<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The beast that was, &amp; is not, &amp; yet is, looked upon: or, The bo-peeping beast pointed at: or, He that hideth himself hunted because of whom truth complaineth, and is spoken to by Pope and Prelate, by Presbyter, by Independent, by Quaker, by Baptist: together with her several answers to them all. Also one description of the beast. Also the coming forth and progress of the beast hitherto. Also an epistle to magistrates and law-givers, likewise, to take off prejudice if any be. Two epistles, one to the reader, and another to the Christian reader. VVith a true reproof to W.S. a Quaker, who in his book called The lying spirit in the mouth of the false prophet, wherein he endeavours to make men believe that he had answered H.H. his book, called The doctrine of the light within the natural man leading to eternal life, examined by Scripture-light.</title>
            <author>Howet, Enoch.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3151</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215400</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827294</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827294</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31711</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31711)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1890:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The beast that was, &amp; is not, &amp; yet is, looked upon: or, The bo-peeping beast pointed at: or, He that hideth himself hunted because of whom truth complaineth, and is spoken to by Pope and Prelate, by Presbyter, by Independent, by Quaker, by Baptist: together with her several answers to them all. Also one description of the beast. Also the coming forth and progress of the beast hitherto. Also an epistle to magistrates and law-givers, likewise, to take off prejudice if any be. Two epistles, one to the reader, and another to the Christian reader. VVith a true reproof to W.S. a Quaker, who in his book called The lying spirit in the mouth of the false prophet, wherein he endeavours to make men believe that he had answered H.H. his book, called The doctrine of the light within the natural man leading to eternal life, examined by Scripture-light.</title>
                  <author>Howet, Enoch.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 64, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Daniel White, at the seven Stars in Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: H.H. i.e. Enoch Howet.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>W. S. --  Lying spirit in the mouth of the false prophet --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31711:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BEAST That was, &amp; is not, &amp; yet is, looked upon: OR, The Bo-peeping Beaſt POINTED AT: OR, He that hideth himſelf hunted, becauſe of whom Truth complaineth, and is ſpoken to by Pope and Prelate, by Presbyter, by Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, by Quaker, by Baptiſt: TOGETHER With her ſeveral Anſwers to them all.</p>
            <p>ALSO One DESCRIPTION of the BEAST.</p>
            <p>ALSO The coming forth and progreſs of the BEAST hitherto.</p>
            <p>ALSO An Epiſtle to Magiſtrates and Law-givers, likewiſe, to take off Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice if any be.</p>
            <p>Two Epiſtles, one to the Reader, and another to the Chriſtian Reader.</p>
            <p>VVITH A true Reproof to <hi>W. S.</hi> a Quaker, who in his Book called <hi>The Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit in the Mouth of the Falſe Prophet,</hi> wherein he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to make Men believe that he had anſwered <hi>H. H.</hi> his Book, called <hi>The Doctrine of the Light within the Natural Man leading to Eternal Life, examined by Scripture-Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Daniel White,</hi> at the ſeven Stars in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:31711:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:31711:2"/>
            <head>Truth ſpeaketh.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have been deſpis'd &amp; baniſh'd from one place to another in the world, ever ſince <hi>Adam</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained a lye for ſelf-exaltation ſake, and ſo fell from me his covering, unto Fig-leaves, and brought his poſterity under <hi>Excuſes</hi> and <hi>May-bees</hi> for their ſouls food and comfort; ſo that a Tabernacle hath been ever ſince more proper for me then a ſettled condition.</p>
            <p>When the true One, the ſent One was upon the earth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſcorn and ſufferings, he did exalt me, and gave Apoſtles and Prophets for Maſter-builders of me upon the chief Corner-ſtone, <hi>viz.</hi> Himſelf, his Death, his Burial, Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Aſcenſion, ſending down his Spirit, which formerly inſpired Scripture-Writers and Believers to joyn his in one Spirit, by which he is preſent in the heart by faith, keeping life eternal in them, and hiding it in God for them, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3. He, I ſay, and his Apoſtles, left my Teſtimony in Scripture-writ, under a terrible charge that none ſhould add to it, nor take from it.</p>
            <p>But as Chriſt and his Apoſtles did, ſo to this day all that will have me without mixture of mans inventions, muſt be ſure to ſuffer; for whoſoever will cloſely walk in my ways, he ſhall loſe friend after friend, as he attaineth to more and knowledge of me: if he be a way faring man, and follow his knowledge heartily and ſincerely, the harder he preſſeth after the mark, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14. the more he encreaſeth in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to the loſs of all or moſt of his friends whom he dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loveth, to the rending of his ſoul; ſo that <hi>he who encreaſeth knowledge, encreaſeth ſorrow,</hi> Eccleſ. 1.18. Yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, this ſorrow could not ſtop the love of Chriſt in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31711:3"/>
hearts of multitudes from keeping his commandments for ſome hundreds of years together after his Aſcention, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.15. though few or none now dare look at me, becauſe there is ſo many of mine enemies that have put upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a dead image of me under forms of godlineſs.</p>
            <p>And alſo another ſort of mine enemies have received the ſpirit of Satan as an Angel of Light, to cry down forms of Godlineſs with; ſo that I cannot appear beautiful in form and power joyntly, as I did in the time of Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and for hundreds of years after: The one of theſe ſorts being offended at my life, becauſe they think to enjoy me coldly, careleſly, eaſily, onely in form; and when that is obtained, they think they may ſleep under the covering of <hi>May-be,</hi> and other excuſes, without diſturbance of ſelf-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation or luſts.</p>
            <p>The other, exalting a ſpirit of deceit to the outing of all, yea the very form of godlineſs, in which the diſtinct order and commands are, That Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught, practiſed and recorded in holy writ for our admonition up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom <hi>the ends of the world are come,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.11. that there may be <hi>As it is written,</hi> to reprove ſin and Satan with, and all reproveable ſpirits and things with, to comfort the diſtreſſed with, to reprove ruleleſs walkers with. This form and record being cryed down, this ſpirit of deceit may rule without examination or reproof; and whatſoever he dictates in the children of diſobedience (for diſobedience is a denying of Gods order) he may call it the moving of Gods ſpirit.</p>
            <p>At the firſt, (before the depths of Satan was known) there was no other grief upon the ſincere ones for Chriſts ſake, but the worlds ſore perſecution; but now this is the worlds wo, they can no ſooner look towards me for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, but one of the two foreſaid <hi>ſtumbling-blocks</hi> or <hi>offences</hi> puts themſelves in the way, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.7.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:31711:3"/>
               <head>Now followeth the ſpeech that may be aptly ſpoken by Pope or Prelate.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Truth,</hi> I hope you will not out me of my honourable order that hath continued about thirteen hundred years, and hath been ſettled by the approbation of ſo many learned and reverend Biſhops and Doctors, who have gone on to chuſe an univerſal Biſhop as Chriſts Vicegerent, reſembling the high Prieſt under the Law, and being <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſour, and have ſettled an attendance of eminent Cardinals that are all Princes, and are able by Authority of our holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to controul Kings and Kingdoms. That hath conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted divers Counſels, and in every Counſel hath brought forth ſome holy Law or Ceremony, or more that maketh for the honour of the Church, and faſt binding her toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſtrength and riches, ſo that now ſhe is become grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſtronger then any Prince, yea, then all the Princes in this part of the world called <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſhe hath invented ſuch Inquiſitions, Racks, Fires, Tortures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and hath ſo abſolute a power, that both the greatneſs of Kingſhip and Nobility, and alſo the baſeneſs of Whores and Harlots, and all luſtful people; yea, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Thieves in Jayl, and Bawdes in Bridewel, have love to my Order; yea, and great reaſon they have, for I can (for money or love, if they be obedient to their Mother holy Church) grant pardons (that will quiet their conſciences if they will believe me) of all their ſins paſt, preſent and to come: ſo that (ſafely be it ſpoken) ſaving the honour of the Church, they have a petty licence to vaunting pride and youthful luſts, being but venial ſins; and all this honour and greatneſs is the fruits of learning and ſtudy, which (as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> writeth) is very laborious <note n="*" place="margin">It is not the ſweat of the brows that God appointed man to get his living by.</note>.</p>
               <p>By my wiſdom I have provided away for younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Noble-men and Knights to creep under my wings for honour and greatneſs; therefore all the greatneſs in this part of the world, will hold me up, and help me to jerk any ſaucy fellow that ſhall hold an Argument (though never
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31711:4"/>
ſo true) againſt me; yea, and if we were cruel (as I hope you will not ſay we are) I have made ſuch proviſion of can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor to luſt, honour and greatneſs in me, that all the honour, ſtrength and multitudes are at my command, to tear the limbs as with their talents, and to bill out the brains (as with my Peak) of all contradictors; inſomuch, that none can open his eye to diſcover my vanity, but a Sword lyeth on it. <hi>Zac.</hi> 11.17.</p>
               <p>I beſeech you alſo take notice of the good I have done for this part of the world who are my Vaſſals: I have buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their Churches, and dedicated them to Chriſt, or one Saint or other, that they may be holy; I have divided their Lands into Pariſhes, ſettled Tithes upon them, left no means unthought out that may dignifie or diſtinguiſh them, but have made all conveniences for eaſe, pleaſure and ſafety that the wit of man can invent. Tell me now, am not I a better Maſter to mine, then Chriſt was to his? Who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered his to be under cruel <hi>mockings, ſcornings, bonds, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, ſavings aſunder, temptings,</hi> being ſlain with <hi>ſwords,</hi> and <hi>wandring up and down in ſheep-skins and goat-skins,</hi> Rom. 16.33. Heb. 11.37. And no marvel; for he had no King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of this world as I have,<note place="margin">But w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilſt thou lookeſt on the Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s outward condition, thou feeleſt not his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>t, <hi>Prov. 1.10.</hi>
                  </note> nor whereon to lay his head; he was never born to that honour and riches that I and mine are, for he was fain to make ſhift with a Manger at the time of his birth: though we aroſe from out of his Charts, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.30. we have attained to greater riches and intail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſtrong ſettlements in this world, then he, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his had or will have.</p>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Truth ſpeaketh.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prelate,</hi> what I ſay to thee, I ſhall ſay to all thy iſſue, <hi>viz.</hi> If thou be not found in the Scriptures of truth, I cannot own thee; for then thou muſt be of mans invention of lies, and muſt be outed for ever having ſhare of me; your Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity cannot maintain you, you are not older then the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of <hi>Jude, verſ.</hi> 4. who wrote of your old Ordination, and your coming in; neither can the approbation of Biſhops
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31711:4"/>
and Doctors juſtifie you, for Chriſt Jeſus thanketh his Father that he hath hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and revealed them to babes. 'Tis not honourableneſs that will help you, for <hi>God will ſtain the pride of all grory, and bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to contempt all the honourable of the earth,</hi> Iſa. 23.9.</p>
                  <p>Whereas you pleade your Councils, I cannot own them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the Scripture of truth concludes them under a wo (<hi>Iſai.</hi> 30.1.) for taking Counſel, and not by Gods Spirit. One thing wherein your Councils are point-blank againſt the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures of truth, is, A Biſhop (the Scripture proveth) muſt be the Governour of a natural family conſiſting of wife and children, where the ſpirit of Government muſt be fruitful in governing his own houſe well, in theſe words, <hi>A Biſhop muſt be blameleſs, the husband of one wife,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Tim. 3.2. <hi>One that ruleth well, having his Children in ſubjection with all gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity; for if he know not how to rule his own, how ſhall he take care of the Church of God? Even ſo muſt their wives be grave,</hi> &amp;c. verſ. 4, 5. And in <hi>Titus, If any man be blameleſs, the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of one wife, having faithful children, not accuſed of ryot or unruly,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>But your Councils are ſo ſhameleſs, that they give out their <hi>Muſt be</hi> againſt the Scriptures <hi>Muſt-be;</hi> for you ſay, That a Biſhop muſt be unmarried, and ſo are all your Prieſts to be by your Councils Order: Therefore let all men look upon thee as one that vieth it with God himſelf; and indeed, if the Scripture had not ſpoken of a falſe-dealing ſhameleſs Clergie, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.15. I ſhould have more admired your impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency: your daughter Presbytery is not altogether ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, for ſhe puts her <hi>May-be</hi> againſt the Scriptures <hi>Muſt-be;</hi> for ſhe ſaith, <hi>A Biſhop may be unmarried.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as for your fixing your ſelf in the joynts of honour, riches, ſtrength, cruelty, multitudes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I muſt by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures of truth tell thee, That <hi>the ſtone, the tryed ſtone, the precious corner-ſtone, when he ſhall lay judgement to the line, and righteouſneſs to the plummet, the hail ſhall ſweep away all your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge of lies, then your contract with hell and death ſhall not ſtand,</hi> Iſai. 28.16. viz. <hi>All this will I give thee if thou wilt fall down and worſhip me.</hi> He that contracted with you, will then prove but a bad Pay-maſter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:31711:5"/>And as concerning the people that is with you in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, this very thing is the curſe that is upon them, <hi>viz.</hi> There ſhall be like people like prieſt, and both in love with lies: if ſometimes the Nation that is called <hi>Gods people</hi> were in this condition, it is eaſily believed that <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>England</hi> may be ſo; It is ſaid of them, <hi>The prophets propheſie falſly, the prieſts bear rule by their means, and my people love to have it ſo: but what will you do in the end thereof?</hi> Theſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, I have done with the Prelate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now followeth the ſpeech that may be aptly ſpokenly ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me of that Presbitery, that is the Prelates Daughter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Truth,</hi> (it is a folly to lye before thee, though I may cozen the people with ſophiſtical Arguments, my learning being very uſeful to me for that purpoſe) I have not ſhaken off my Mothers foundation, but have kept her Baptiſm, her ſticking to mans Ordination to preach, though not wholly in her Order; for I tell you truly, herein lyeth my pomp, my riches, my benefice, my pariſh-livings that my Mother Prelate provided for me, and is the very Saddle upon which I ride the Beaſt, by the help of my brother Lawyer, (which Beaſt ſome have interpreted to be the great powers of the earth) for I know, the ſame ſpirit that cauſed the Hierarchies ſucceſſors to ordain me, will cauſe them to maintain me, and all my honours and greatneſs; for indeed, I have all the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and great ones power, (for few or none of the Rulers believe on poor Chriſt, and his poor deſpiſed people) and therefore I flatter them in their powdered locks and new faſhions,<note place="margin">Rom. 12. gives you no ſuch warrant.</note> and their wives in their long trailing Gowns, naked Breaſts, and ſpotted Faces; or if I flatter them not, I make my reproofs ſo ſoft and ſo thin as the Tiffany they wear. And for their filth of meat and vain talk, I ſmile at them, whilſt I formally reprove them, and I call it not Gluttony and Drunkenneſs, neither do I charge it ſo ſtrictly upon them to face them with bold reproofs, telling them, That for every
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31711:5"/>
idle word they muſt give an account at the day of judgment, as the poor ſilly followers of poor Chriſt do.</p>
               <p>Alas, poor ſouls! for their plain dealing, the world judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them accurſed, and turneth them out of doors; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I can be welcome to great perſons, and we can call on another godly; lying, till we think we ſay truly: and both of us together fall upon the back of the poor ſilly followers of poor Chriſt; by which means it is no diſgrace to me up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, before the great ones, and the luſtful ones, and the common people; though the foreſaid poor people by plain proofs cut of Scripture make me naked.</p>
               <p>My Mothet <hi>Prelate</hi> hath provided for me an example, <hi>viz.</hi> to flee to the Authority of Fathers; which (though they will not clearly ſerve my turn) yet my Rhetorick and Learning, together with the help of my brother <hi>Lawyer,</hi> who is my Companion in Learning, and a good Orator both in Courts and Countrey, yea before Princes he will plead for me. The Scribes and Phariſees (<hi>viz.</hi> Prieſts and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers) were ever Companions, and Enemies to Chriſt and his poor Flock. However, in theſe two particulars my Brother <hi>Lawyer</hi> and I differ; they (though as Learned as I) let down themſelves to ſpeak as plainly and homely as may be, that the Country Juries may underſtand them, and ſo do juſtice: But I, for maintaining my Livings, Dignities, and eſteem amongſt men, am conſtrained to hide my ſelf in the words of Art, and abſtruſe Phraſes, as <hi>Divinity, and Habits of Grace,</hi> &amp;c. that I may be as ſlippery as an Eel, when plain Country underſtanding would catch me, and have a hole to creep out when the plain ſimple wiſdom and the truth of theſe <hi>Nazae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites</hi> hath incloſed me.</p>
               <p>The ſecond thing wherein my Brother <hi>Lawyer</hi> and I dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. They may be in their callings, and Diſciples of Chriſt, too, (provided they be not inſtruments of cruelty, but uſe honeſt Laws, honeſtly) as <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> and <hi>Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> was, &amp;c. but I (if I ſhould be of the Sect of the <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,</hi> every where ſpoken againſt) muſt loſe both my Honour and Greatneſs, (what great men purchaſed by flattery) and by ſilence at their vanities, and all my fat Livings: and let the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31711:6"/>
World judge whether it were wiſdom ſo to do.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>And the truth is (though I be not altogether ſo honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in name as my Mother, yet) I think my ſelf ſtronger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Hypocrites, and ſelf-ſeeking Profeſſors; for by how much I am eſteemed Godly, by ſo much thoſe are eſteemed ugly that cannot joyn with me. And upon this account I have more reaſon (in the eyes of all our Fraternity, that ſeek honour one of another) to perſecute any ſaucy <hi>Jack,</hi> that upon pretence of Scripture-plainneſs is dare reprove us, or caſt contempt upon our Rhetorical Tropes or figures, which are as ſilk Gowns to honour us, before an ignorant Multitude, eſpecially if we can foi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out a little Latin, which (though this our learning, together with Mans Ordination, maketh us to ſtand to it, that we are to be preferred before Mechanicks, and ſo are holier then they, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.5. though we be a ſtink in Gods Noſe, and a fire that burneth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the day) maketh us a ſweet ſent in the noſe of an ignorant multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; for becauſe we are Learned, they think they may be hold to truſt us, and ſo by this very means, they think they need not rave into what we ſay, as the <hi>Bereans</hi> did, but take all upon truſt, and ſo are kept ignorant, and dwell at eaſe ſtill. And now tell me, <hi>Truth,</hi> if thou canſt approve of theſe things, I ſhall live bravely both here and hereafter.</p>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Truth ſpeaketh.</head>
                  <p>As I ſay to thy Mother <hi>Prelate,</hi> ſo I ſay to thee, Except thy Image or ſuperſcription be found in the Scriptures of Truth, thou art but of mans invention, which God hateth, <hi>Iſa</hi> 66.3. and alſo the refuge of lies, which muſt be ſwept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: Thy Mothers name is <hi>MYSTERY, BABYLON THE GREAT, THE MOTHER OF HARLOTS, AND ABO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MINATIONS OF THE VVHOLE EARTH,</hi> Rev. 17.1. It is notorious, that ſhe beareth her name in her forehead; which proveth, 1. She is aſhamed of nothing. 2. That every one may apparently behold her Abominations in her Forehead. And now let us ſee how like thy Mother thou art.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:31711:6"/>1. Thou and thy Mother have all one baptiſm, which paſs from one to another by the Proclamation of Princes, but not by Gods word; which proveth you both to be of Mans Generation and Maintenance; whereas a Proclamation had power to make you both the Religious legitimate Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren one of another: All thy Children were made thy Mothers, by Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Proclamation; all thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Children were made thine, by King <hi>Edward</hi>'s and Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Proclamations. The truth is, you are of ſuch a Brood, and ſo neer of Kin, that you cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted one to another by preaching Faith, Repentance and Baptiſm, but being both of a nature, and depending both up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Man, a Proclamation can command the one to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Proteſtant upon the Papiſts Baptiſm, and the other to be a Chriſtian Papiſt upon the Proteſtants Baptiſm.</p>
                  <p>In your Infancy, when you were Cozened inſtead of Chriſtened (as you call it) you were proclaimed Regenerate and born again, made a Child of God, and an Inheritor of the Kingdom of Heaven, when you could neither under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Doctrine with your hearts, whereby Man believeth unto Righteouſneſs; nor with your Mouthes confeſs unto Salvation, <hi>Rom</hi> 10.10. for you could not ſpeak to confeſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing. Is any of your Laws like the Law of God in this, which proclaimeth Faith comes by hearing? <hi>How ſhall they believe on whom they have not heard? and how ſhall they hear without a Preacher?</hi> The aforeſaid brazen-fac'd Act ſtandeth by thy Mothers Canon-Law, and all thy oldeſt Prieſts that took Degrees in the Univerſitie, though godly in thy eſteem) are ſworn to obſerve all the Rights and Ceremonies of holy Church; which Canon Law intendeth the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> then conſider whoſe ſworn ſervants thy prieſts are. And now conſider (I pray thee) whether thou haſt not a brow of Braſs, in not being aſhamed, though all the world (that are not Members with thee) behold thy Whoredoms, and thy Abominations written in thy forehead.</p>
                  <p>Now out with thy Learning, thy Rhetorical Tropes and Figures; call for thy brother Lawyer, and all the power of the Magiſtrate, and all the luſtful Multitude, that loveth to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31711:7"/>
hear and believe lies (thou haſt nothing elſe to feed them with, but what is mix'd with lies: and indeed, Truth would be ſo bitter, that neither thou nor they could bear it, if you did not ſweeten it, or rather fit it to your palate with lies) and ſee if they all can cover from reproof out of Gods word, by the mouth of poor mechanick deſpiſed <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his poor mechanick deſpiſed Apoſtles and Diſciples.</p>
                  <p>Alſo thou forceſt thy maintenance by mans Law, from thoſe that thou ſoweſt no ſpiritual ſeed in their hearts: if there were ſpiritual things betwixt Prieſt and People, it would make ſuch a product of love, that the Royal Law of Heaven, Chriſts Church, Saints, Angels, Chriſt, and God the Father, as would procure the Prieſts maintenance from their Converts, they need not go to mans Law to get it, if thou hadſt ſome few Converts. Thou doſt like him that ſoweth two or three Lands in a field onely, and yet challengeth the whole field; though there be hundreds of Lands upon which none of thy ſeed is ſown, and ſueſt and undoeſt thy poor neighbours if they will not yeild thee their increaſe out of the whole field. Doſt thou look for fruit when all thy ſeed is rotten under the Clods, and bringeth up none? Is not this thy Mothers name written on thy forehead? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Will the Scriptures own thee in this? Is it fit that thou ſhouldſt reap that fruit by violence, that came not of thy ſeed?</p>
                  <p>Again, did not <hi>Jeroboam</hi> carry all the ten Tribes from Gods Worſhip to the calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> onely to ſave his honour, kingdom and ſtanding? Doth not <hi>Edward, George</hi> and <hi>Richard,</hi> and all the godly Prieſts in <hi>England,</hi> know. That no Scripture-reproof can lye upon the Baptizer or Baptized, where Faith and Repentance is ſincerely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed before the performance of that Ordinance? And alſo that there is never a word to ſay (in Scripture) for their Infants Baptiſm but a <hi>May-be?</hi> Upon ſuch an aſſurance they will not venture to buy twenty pounds worth of Land: And this their <hi>May-be</hi> is but imagined, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all warrant of Scripture. Do they not now caſt the Anchor of their Rhetorick and Learning into any Lie or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31711:7"/>
                     <hi>May-be,</hi> to keep their Kingdom their Mother Prelate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them by Pope and Councils, they having never a word of God to prove Gods <hi>Muſt-be</hi> or commandment for their practice? And doth not all their <hi>May bees</hi> ariſe from Popes, Councils and Fathers, whoſe beings would fall, their honour ceaſe, and none would buy their wares any more, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.11. compared with the laſt words of verſ. 13. if they did not (<hi>Jereboam</hi> like) hold the People from the worſhip of God recorded in the Scriptures of Truth?</p>
                  <p>Have they not procured the Armour of the Magiſtrates Power to protect them, that none may ſpeak in their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick places, nor ſpeak to diſturb them? Oh! what a Licenſe is here to tell lies without reproof, while they are going to, or coming from thence! but their own Learned Rhetorical, by man ordained Members; that are faſt tied, not by Truth, but by the bonds of their own Livings and greatneſs, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving entertained that Temptation, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> refuſed, <hi>viz.</hi> all the Kingdoms of the world, and the glory thereof; therefore His Servants are not payed for His VVork out of the world's common ſtock, of Honour, Greatneſs, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings of a hundred, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a year; nor hath <hi>Chriſts</hi> Servants the flock of Knights, Ladies and Gentles, in their ſilk Gowns trailing on the ground, to ſeek them for their good eſteem, as thou haſt, even as thy Mother <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Prelate</hi> hath, for their bleſſings: But <hi>Sion</hi> is an out-caſt in this world; <hi>This is Sion whom no man ſeeketh after, Jer.</hi> 30.7. It is the ſuppoſed know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the learned Phariſees, together with the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his brother, and the ſuppoſed ignorance of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Flock; <hi>Doth any of the Phariſees or the Rulers</hi> (who are Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers) <hi>believe on him, but this people who know not the Law,</hi> and <hi>are accurſed?</hi> VVhilſt thou art overcome with the aforeſaid temptation, therein being an enemy to all Righteouſneſs, in not ceaſing to pervert the right wayes of God, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.10. The very thing that becometh <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and all that he calleth us to fulfil, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.15. which are plain Scripture-Precepts; and in ſetting thy <hi>May-bees</hi> in the room thereof. Theſe things conſidered, I leave thee, <hi>Presbyter,</hi> to judge thy ſelf by the 13 <hi>Chapter</hi> of <hi>Ezekiel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:31711:8"/>
                  <head>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sbyter may thus Reply.</head>
                  <p>I ſtrange at your reproof, being my name is recorded in the Scriptures, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. I confeſs that is a proper name, and a name fit for Diſciples, made and baptized by <hi>Chriſt</hi> or His diſciples. I judge thee not for the name thou beareſt, but for thy Nature and Generation, as thou art <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Prelates</hi> Daughter; thoſe that are called by the foreſaid name in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re, had the nature of the name<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thy nature is of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>er, <hi>Myſtery, Babylon the great, the Mother of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, and abominations of the whole earth;</hi> my confederates are VVarriors againſt the Lamb, the place where thou fitteſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Peoples, Multitudes,</hi> &amp;c. the name aforeſaid to thee is the ſheeps clothing, that thy wolviſh nature is covered with, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15. this nature of thine appeareth cruel, in that thou art a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> enmity with thy Mother <hi>Prelate,</hi> and thy Mother with thee; like two Boars with their Tuſhes in each others ſides, whilſt both of you deſire to lay Gods Vineyard waſte; like two wild Beaſt that are deſtroying one another, and all that com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> you: as if you did reſemble the two paws of that B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar, ſacken of in the Scriptures of Truth, that had three ribs in her m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uths <hi>Dan.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 5. whoſe ribs they were, is not named intimating, that it matter'd not to her whoſe ſides ſhe tore in pieces, ſo ſhe might devour much fleſh; the three ribs ſomething reſembling the treble damage that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth men to great diſtreſs,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> this beaſt being reſolved to tear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll in pieces, rather then to want her Prey.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ſheep of Chriſt (whoſe clothing you have put on in that Name) look in their mouths, there is no tooth in their heads that can draw blood of their fellow creatures; their food is that which they can eat without hurting their fellow creatures: a beaſt, a horſe and a ſheep may feed in one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e without hurting one another: Their ſhepherd did not teach them to perſecute men for conformity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>though they had to do with a falſe deceiving and deceived people, <hi>blinde leaders of the blind,</hi> Mat. 15.14.) that diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from them, but directs them to let them alone; and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31711:8"/>
when there was men caſting out devils, and followed not them, <hi>forbid them not,</hi> ſaith their ſhepherd, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.5. <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.39. As it is againſt the nature of a ſheep to run after a wolf to worry him, ſo it is againſt the nature of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Chriſts Kingdom, to run after Errours and Hereſies with Fire, Sword Death, Priſons and Whips in their hand; there is no ſuch tools in Chriſts Kingdom; of the encreaſe of his government and peace there ſhall be no <hi>end,</hi> Iſa. 9.7. Here, here in this place, I ſay, is the food and joy of their ſouls! whilſt this brood of <hi>Myſtery Babylon</hi> have no ſoul-food or content, except they may have a whip and other tortures in their hand to drive their neighbours into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity. Thus going about to build up <hi>Sion</hi> with blood, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with iniquity, <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.10. and the chief rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this their violence, is, their heart is ſo fraught with pride and covetouſneſs, that they cannot endure any <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decal</hi> who will not give them honour, nor any piece of hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry that will not yeild them tenths or compoſition; and this maketh them (<hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>man</hi>-like) to run to the Magiſtrate when they conceive themſelves wronged in this caſe. Look to thy ſelf, Presbytery, I may not own thee for the body of Chriſt, becauſe thou art not recorded in the Scriptures of Truth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now followeth the ſpeech which ſome Independ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts, Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child to Pope and Prelate, and daughter to Presbyter, may aptly ſpeak.</head>
               <p>I have called my mother Harlot, and have left her as ſuch a one; though ſhe be a well favoured-one, ſhe is the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all Nations and Families where ſhe is, through her witchcrafts, <hi>Nahum</hi> 3.4. bewitching people upon a religions account, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</p>
               <p>I have none of her prieſts compelled maintenance, though ſome of us think our ſelves happy for having a Levite to our Prieſt, <hi>viz.</hi> one of thoſe the Clergy were wont to pray for, <hi>viz.</hi> the whole Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> by what name or title ſoever
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31711:9"/>
they were dignified or diſtinguiſhed, <hi>Judg.</hi> 17.13. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we would not be too far ſeparated from our Mother, we love her a little; ſhe may ſtrengthen us, and we her; we would have a little of her worldly eſteem: though the rude Multitude own us not, in time we may be as much honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for Godlineſs as our Grandmother and Mother is, for their ability to prefer to ſetled honour and riches, and for their flattery, eaſe and luſts: but we doubt we have a little of our Mothers pride, and willingneſs to ſave our skins, therefore we will be modeſtly Godly; and that with ſo much wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as may keep as much of our mothers love, and our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers friends as we can: Alſo we have Paſtors of our own chuſing, and ſome of us have Paſtors that have no Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from man, nor deſcent from mans Authority; yet we have our Grandmother and our Mothers baptiſm, by vertue of the Popes Decree, it was given to our Mothers Mother, and ſo we have that from Antiquity and Succeſſion: If we ſhould by denyal of that, tear our ſelves from our Ancient Worſhip, and deny the worlds Baptiſm, and unchriſtian them all at once <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>, we ſhould loſe (all at once) our relation and hopes of worldly promotion.</p>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Truth ſpeaketh.</head>
                  <p>To have a neer Relation to me onely in ſimilitude, will not make thee in Union with me; to be almoſt a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (like <hi>Agrippa</hi>) is to be no Chriſtian, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.28. To be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in heaven, and go no further, is never to come there; there is many who undertake to counterfeit me, but there is no likeneſs in all things of me, but my ſelf: but the Counterfeits are in ſomething lame, or in ſomething ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous: I agree with all and every command of God in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and there is room for nothing elſe in me, but what Scripture will own.</p>
                  <p>The Scriptures of Truth doth not clearly own you, the Scripture clearly owneth, that, upon believing, men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ought to be, and were baptized, and walk together in Church-order; of this there is many witneſſes throughout the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31711:9"/>
new Teſtament, as Act. 8. and Act. 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but not one witneſs that unbaptized perſons walked in Church order, or that Infants was commanded to be (or was) baptized: of the firſt there is certainty, neither thou, nor all the Learned Rabbies in the world can deny it; of the ſecond there is but a <hi>May-be,</hi> and that from mans inventions.</p>
                  <p>I charge you all, and all that reads this writing, as you fear God, to ſearch the Scripture, and ſee if in this particular you can attain to a better proof then a <hi>May-be;</hi> if thou canſt not, be aſhamed, and repent, for I look at thee to have more ſhame in thee, then either thy Grandmother or thy Mother, and preſume not above what is written: you need do no more then Scripture warranteth you, it hath enough in it (if obſerved in Letter and Spirit) to furniſh the man of God throughly to perfection and all good works, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then lay aſide all your Ordinances that are grounded upon <hi>May-be,</hi> though the wiſeſt men that ever were in the world invented them; O conſider God will take Vengeance on inventions, though they be of <hi>Moſes, Aaron</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> Pſal. 99.6. to verſ. 8. Conſider alſo that mans inventions diverteth him from his Uprightneſs, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29.</p>
                  <p>And whereas yon tell me of chuſing Paſtors your ſelves, let me tell you, Paſtors and Teachers are given by God, and not choſen by men; and except it be found in Scriptures of Truth, that man is directed to chuſe any ſuch Officers, take heed leſt thou erect an Idol of thine own invention in ſo doing, inſtead of following Gods direction. God knoweth well thou canſt nor chuſe as God chuſeth, for man looketh at the outward appearance (<hi>viz.</hi> a man that delivereth well-compoſed words) but the Lord knoweth the heart; take heed leſt thoſe that thou haſt choſen (building upon their choice) ſilence thoſe Paſtors which God hath given, and that are gifted by God: Thou art no more able to chuſe a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor for thy ſelf, then a company of School-boyes are to chuſe a wiſe, learned Maſter: therefore God no where in Scripture put the choice of Paſtor into thy hands: I adviſe thee, take it not: It is true, that a company of men who have followed Chriſt in the Regeneration, in Faith, Repentance,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31711:10"/>
Baptiſm, and (in the Form) have the Spirit and Life, have heard and learned of the Father, and have the Son revealed in them; even as the outward skin of the body, and the inwards, as Heart, Mind, Members, are all imbodied, and preſented to our Underſtanding in one Body, ſo Form and Power, living Faith, and Repentance, and prevailing Prayer, which makes us as <hi>Iſrael, viz</hi> a Prince prevailing with God; like as the Tree and Fruit, the Sap and the Rinde, ſo Gods Order and Life are not to be ſeparated, but are one in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brought forth: The Form obeyed being the Creatures Duty, Life in the Form being Gods owning or acceptance in the Creature, like a golden Sceptre ſtretched forth by God, and like a ſeal of <hi>God,</hi> ſet upon the creatures heart, which maketh his heart merry, the joy of the Lord being his ſtrength, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 1.13. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.10. A company of ſuch men (I ſay) that ſo have entrance into the Kingdom of <hi>God, viz.</hi> that have ſubmitted to his Government, receiving the new birth of water and the Spirit in baptiſm, and all the following com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands recorded in the written word (that great <hi>Charter</hi> being their Law, without mixture of mans inventions, and thereby owning <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be their <hi>Lord,</hi> and themſelves to be inchartered Citizens, he ruling over them (not like thoſe recorded in <hi>Luke</hi> 19.14. by the ſame <hi>Charter</hi>) have authority to chuſe two ſorts of Officers for ordering of the outward man: but a Paſtor is a higher thing, it is a gift of <hi>God,</hi> a heart-feeding gift, <hi>viz</hi> Biſhops and Deacons, the one to keep the <hi>Church</hi> in order, the other to take care of the poors ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities to relieve them; whoſe bowels of tender-hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs have appeared to their natural Relations; whoſe wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath been fruitful in governing by love; theſe may be choſen by mans Election, if there be any that have the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification the Scripture layeth down, not elſe; as in <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.6. <hi>If any be blameleſs.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>There is no haſte in chuſing what <hi>God</hi> hath not marked out; If <hi>God</hi> hath not given thee men of ſuch qualifications, as he approveth on, thou hadſt better be without Governors lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, then to ſet up Antichriſt in <hi>Chriſts</hi> chair: In this ſenſe, <hi>He that believeth maketh not haſte,</hi> Iſa. 28.16. <hi>viz.</hi> to act
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31711:10"/>
without his Guiders rule. The name of a Biſhop hath the nature of his Office included into it, which is <hi>ruling</hi> and <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſight;</hi> aptneſs to teach is but a qualification, that any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Member may have, in whom the Spirit of God doth or ſhall breath, being a truth-evidencing, and forceable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and cannot ſtay for leave of Election by man to utter it ſelf, which indeed is a gift of God, or Paſtoral Spirit; as Marriage is another qualification wherein the ſpirit of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment muſt appear fruitful both in wife and children, and that from conjugal and natural love to the Yoak fellow, and procreated (in which affections Faith appeareth, and for want of them, infidelity, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5 8.) ſo that children cannot be wanting to a Biſhop, in whoſe government, the Royal Law (Love) of <hi>Gods Church</hi> is reſembled, Marriage being the Type of Chriſt and his Church; and it is certain that a batche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, or one that hath no children, or one whoſe wife and children are not qualified according to the word, cannot be choſen, except man will ſet his <hi>May-be</hi> againſt <hi>Gods Muſt-be:</hi> And ſo I leave thee <hi>Independant,</hi> warning thee to take the counſel of Chriſt to the Angel of the Church of <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea,</hi> Rev. 3.17.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Speech that may be aptly ſpoken by theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> who hold forth a ſtupifying Spirit, denying plain Truth, and right Reaſon, under the Notion of a higher Mystery and Spirit then plain Scripture and right Reaſon will admit of; which plain Scripture they call Letter, and right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they call Fleſh, in contempt; notwithſtanding that the Spirit of God is promiſed to be poured into him that turneth at Gods Reproof, <hi>Prov. 1.23.</hi> which Reproof convinceth Reaſon, or elſe man could not return: into Reaſon, among the reſt of the Souls Members, the Spirit was poured, and is wrought upon to order Mans Affairs by Judgement, and doth receive wiſe Counſels, when the man of Underſtanding attaineth to them, <hi>Prov. 1.5.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Truth,</hi> though we may not talk with thee, we are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31711:11"/>
to receive directions by any that is call'd by thy name, nor by the writings called Scriptures of Truth; for what directions ſoever we have from without, can be but mans teachings, and the natural man underſtandeth not the things of <hi>God;</hi> we are taught by the Light within, we are to ſtand in the will of <hi>God,</hi> and obſerve the movings and commands of his Spirit.</p>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Truth ſpeaketh.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> reſembling God's people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> great humility, <hi>Pſal. 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>1.</hi>
                     </note> As in the viſion of <hi>Eſdras,</hi> the Eagles heads ſlept until her Feathers had reigned, as in 2 <hi>Eſd.</hi> 12 25. <hi>Theſe are they that ſhall accompliſh his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and finiſh his laſt end:</hi> even ſo in <hi>Babylon the great, the Mother of Harlots, and abominations of the whole earth,</hi> the heads, and ſubtileſt, and ſtrongeſt of her deluſions ſhe hath kept until her laſt end (which I hope is approaching) that thou who wouldſt not receive the Truth in the love thereof, mightſt not hear the reproof of thy walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in falſe forms any longer, in ſo much that thou couldſt not deny, that if forms muſt be owned, thou muſt come out of them, and come into the form of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Satan hath now cozened thee another way, and thy <hi>AS GOD,</hi> he hath perſwaded thee that all forms muſt be caſt off, and the Law of the Spirit of Life entertained.</p>
                  <p>O cunning and ſubtile, (but falſe deluſions) the words of the Prophets, and the Commandment of the Apoſtles were ſet in oppoſition formerly to luſts, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1, 2. but never to the way of Righteouſneſs by any but theſe laſt members of <hi>Babylon. Peter,</hi> in Chap. 2. 1. &amp; 2. hath theſe words, <hi>And many ſhall follow their pernitious wayes, by reaſon of whom the way of Truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of.</hi> Wherein we may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſee, that their wayes and the wayes of Truth, ſtands in flat oppoſition one to another. Alſo in the firſt verſe it is teſtified, that to <hi>bring in theſe damnable hereſies,</hi> is to <hi>deny the Lord that bought them:</hi> but he himſelf is ſo far from that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in verſe 21. of the ſaid Chapter, that he chargeth the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31711:11"/>
way of Righteouſneſs, and the holy commandments as the very Centre from which Apoſtates fall; ſo that you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold clearly that it is not a Righteouſneſs they are charged for falling from, for that is the ſecret iſſues which is betwixt God and the heart; but the way of Righteouſneſs, which is viſible to the underſtanding of Man.</p>
                  <p>Many of their Leaders, whilſt they were able to hold the Antichriſtian form, they were in the eſteem of godly Prieſts, whoſe infants Baptiſm, and learned, ſpecious Paſtoral care, ſo much applauded by wiſe, ſober, rich, ſilken-coated Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, then (I ſay) not being able to reſiſt the clear evidence that the true form of Godlineſs hath, becauſe they did not love to be diſquieted out of the woman <hi>Jezabels</hi> bed, <hi>Rov.</hi> 2.22. where they lay in pleaſure of imagined Godlineſs, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a company of wiſe, ſober Profeſſors, they were then ſo far from receiving the love of the truth, that they grew into diſquietneſs of mind, and hatred of that form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs that Chriſt and His Apoſtles, and their Diſciples wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in for many years; even (till the time that Antichriſt grew popular) in ſo high a meaſure Satan being ready with this Temptation) that they ſtruck hands with this ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, and ſo believed the lies thereof, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11. that they cryed down all forms, that they might be ſhut of (yea and avenged of) that form, the thoughts whereof ſo much troubled them: if they knew their own hearts, they would ingeniouſly confeſs this.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, whoſoever deſireth further ſatisfaction in this matter, is referred to a Book that the Author hath written, called <hi>The Doctrine of the Light, within the natural man, lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to eternal Life, examined by Scripture Light.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Baptiſt ſpeaketh.</head>
               <p>The Spirit of <hi>God</hi> having inſtructed me by the Scripture, I fell into a courſe of reaſoning, which (though Myſtery <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> cryeth down in this her laſt diſpenſation) being the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> cryeth up, and reproveth the neglect of, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44. on this manner. There is no word for baptizing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31711:12"/>
in Scripture, not no regular account from which that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention can ariſe; it is the very door that the god of this world makes all this part of the world called <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> of one ſuppoſed Faith by: leaving no man at liberty to chuſe his Religion, but maketh the inſtruments of his generation to be that which giveth him right to the Inſtruments of his Regeneration; and as for the new birth, he will have his to preſume that from imagination; and all this to be done when the party ſuppoſed to be baptized could neither aſſent by underſtanding to what was done, nor diſſent by doing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing but crying, which he would have done, if they had gone about to kill him, as to have chriſtened him, as they call it. Alſo herein thoſe err (that have ſchiſm'd from Popery and Prelacy, but hold their baptiſm of Infants) ſaying, That Infants of godly Parents may be baptized; by which words, they acknowledge in effect that the fleſhly copulation of godly Parents giveth right to the children of their natural Body to be inſtruments of Regeneration<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that it muſt needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that there is no need of converſion to make them Chriſtians, who are Chriſtians born by the natural fleſh of their godly Parents, and ſo the god of this world who hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inded their eyes, maketh them eſteem it a great priviledge to have a perfect dead Act of his ſuppoſed Regeneration to be done by force upon their children; for they can have no meanes to know or gueſs that the Spirit is joyned with water in their baptiſm, which is the Inſtrument or outward Act of their Regeneration.</p>
               <p>Conſider how faſt the poor Infant is lock'd to preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, when they have either preſumption or nothing for the Foundation of their Order, or rather Myſtery <hi>Babylon's</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; the god of this world knew well that none could be admitted into the Kingdom of <hi>God,</hi> or government of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> without Regeneration of water and the Spirit; and his buſineſs in Myſtery <hi>Babylon</hi> is to bring man to invent a form in imitation of <hi>God,</hi> and ſo keep men, that when they come to be capable of believing, they ſhould not look after Baptiſm or Regeneration of Water and the Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:31711:12"/>As Chriſt hath His Diſciples made and baptized, ſo <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> Myſtery hath hers, ſuppoſed to be baptized too: and in this the man of ſin exalteth himſelf above God, for God is merciful in forgiving ſins, and receiving into grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, upon Repentance, every penitent ſinner; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath given Order to His Diſciples, upon confeſſion of Faith, and Repentance, to baptize; but this man of ſin will make men believe that he hath more mercy then God by His word holds forth; for he receiveth all in Infancy, and needeth neither Faith nor Repentance in receiving his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: the Subjects of Chriſts Kingdom have heart-pricking Truth to convince them, and bring them to Repentance; but <hi>Babylons</hi> Members are ſo eaſily made, that they neither knew nor felt when it was done: And thus the way is broad and eaſie that leadeth to deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Alſo conſidering that the keeping of Chriſts Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is a proof of our love to Chriſt, and that the receiving of the Spirit is an effect of obedience, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.15, 16. and knowing that the written word is more ſurely to be taken heed to, then an Act of the Spirit in Transfiguration, though Chriſt Himſelf be preſent, 2 <hi>Pet</hi> 2.19. to the end; becauſe Satan being a ſpirit can diſſemble a ſpiritual Act, but his mouth is ſtopped, and he reproved with <hi>It is written.</hi> And further, knowing that Chriſt taught duty from the written word, and it to be believed and practiſed, rather then the words of one which ſhould riſe from the dead, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.22. I ſtayed not for Revelation to teach me my duty; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I expect Revelation to convey unto us, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in us Chriſt our life; but turn'd at Wiſdom's reproof, expecting (after) obedience Wiſdom's promiſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23. And now hating every falſe way, knowing, <hi>They that err from thy Statutes, their deceit is falſehood, Pſal.</hi> 119.118. and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming thy Precepts concerning all things to be right, ver. 128. I cannot but ſay of Scripture record, <hi>Thy word is very pure, therefore my ſoul loveth it,</hi> verſe 140. and upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I took the directions of that Scripture which <hi>Paul</hi> writeth by inſpiration of the Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17, 18. and proveth it by <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.11. <hi>viz. I came out from Babylon My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:31711:13"/>
the great,</hi> her Daughter and Grandchild, and touched none of their precedent manners, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.30. But I ſay, laying aſide mans learned miſts of darkneſs, and his prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Examples, I took the Doctrine of Chriſt and His Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles for my Foundation, and their Enſamples for following of Chriſt for my imitation, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20.</p>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Truth ſpeaketh.</head>
                  <p>I tell thee Church of Chriſt, as thy name is the <hi>houſe of God,</hi> the <hi>Church of the living God,</hi> the <hi>Pillar and Ground of the truth,</hi> thou art not in thy order reproveable by Scriptures, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. And if any Enemy whatſoever undertake to reprove thee, and hath not Chriſts weapon he fought Satan with, <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>z. it is written,</hi> though he tell thee of ſtanding in the Will of God, or being led by the Spirit, or of an inward Teacher, or of Light within, as if there were ſome ſecret thing that paſſed by <hi>peeping</hi> and <hi>muttering,</hi> which right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cannot be uſed about the underſtanding of, they are no better the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>VVizards</hi> or <hi>Familiar Spirits; To the Law and to the Teſtimonies,</hi> if there they miſs any thing (<hi>viz.</hi> in that they hold forth or teach) and ſpeak not according to this word, though they talk of Light within, it is becauſe there is no Light in them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.19, 20. and their light is darkneſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.19. fear thou no ſuch Enemies, but live in the nature of rejoycing, there meet thy God, there work Righteouſneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.5. <hi>viz.</hi> That which Chriſt began and ſhewed us, when he ſaid, <hi>Thus it becometh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.5. Take thou no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the continuance of Gods wayes, though the Enemy would tell thee they are ended: and ſo expect thy Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>And againſt the fear of thoſe that would ſet a Spirit which teacheth not to obey Scriptures, and follow the examples of Chriſt and His Diſciples in oppoſition to a <hi>Spirit</hi> that teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to live in obedience to Scriptures, and to follow the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples aforeſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. Comfort thy ſelf by Faith in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and there with patience caſt the Anchor of thy hope, <hi>Phil.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.4. <hi>Rejoyce alwayes, yea, again I ſay rejoyce.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:31711:13"/>And that thy rejoycing may not be in vain, take theſe Cautions.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Take heed that thou miſs not of a way within a way, if thou bleſs thy ſelf in the high way, without the way which is called holy, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.8. which holy way is recorded in <hi>Job</hi> 28.7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Is the turning up all things by the roots, cutting forth rivers among the rocks, diſcovering every pretious thing, binding the floods from overflowing, bringing forth hidden things to light.</hi> The high way being thy duty to walk in, the holy way being the laying of Gods hand upon Chriſt thy Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and doing all thy works for thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.12. holding thee that thou canſt not depart from him, and quickning the deſires of thy ſoul, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.17, 18. In all thy acts of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, thy Faith muſt be in the operation of God, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. through which our Duties are living Ordinances performed by two co-workers.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Take heed whilſt you walk into the way of God, that your great buſineſs be to ſeek God, His Face, His ſtrength evermore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.3, 4. where the Pſalmiſt maketh this the ground of his joy; therefore (if you fail herein) your joy is groundleſs. In which ſearch love kindleth more and more, as thou comeſt neerer God; ſo as the ſoul groweth ſick of love, and cannot ceaſe to preſs hard after God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.8. becauſe it is upbeld by Gods right hand, till thou know thy ſelf to be ſet as a ſeal upon Chriſts arm and his heart for ever, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6. and then alſo wilt thou follow on to know the Lord, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.3.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Take heed thou be not <hi>defiled in the way,</hi> Pſal. 119.1. for it is leſs offence to bring a beaſtly Creature into a hogſtie, or any filthy place, then to bring it into a Princes preſence-chamber, or a bed of love, where there ought to be nothing loathſome, but all to be lovely, and love pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking Objects: So is it leſs wickedneſs to have a mind and conſcience defiled, in beaſtly prophaneſs, then to bring ſuch a minde into the Houſe of God, <hi>the Church of the living God,</hi> Tim. 1.15. That thy ſoul may bee deeply ingaged, take notice of the whole Order of perſons and things wherein thy communion lies with the Father and his Son
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31711:14"/>
Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3, 4. The whole Order is the <hi>innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable company of Angels, the General Aſſembly of the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, that are written in heaven, unto God the judge of all, unto Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator of the new Covenant, and to the blood of ſprinkling, that ſpeaketh better things then the blood of Abel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the firſt place conſider, whether the Father and the Son can have communion with thy ſins, thy worldly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, or purſued honours? in a condition where right and ſtrong and pure Objects of eternal love, forceth the heart to a ſtrong purgation, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3. No, no, all thy pleaſures, honours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt be thruſt from thee, as a <hi>menſtruous rag.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Conſider, whether ſuch company can delight to talk with thee of good bargains, the honour thou haſt from great perſons, the delicates wherewith thy feaſts are furniſhed, and thy new faſhions: No, no, I tell thee, the mind that can feed on theſe things, is too defiled for Gods ways and can take no pleaſure in Heavenly food; a pure mind is capable of remembrance of the commandments of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.2. of the enjoyning the <hi>commanded loving kindneſs of God,</hi> which hath ſuch warmth and power, that it maketh them become one new heart with this new wine, and Gods <hi>Song with them in the right,</hi> when God uſeth their heart, their joy, and their and his own delight to ſing his ſongs with, and their <hi>prayer with the God of their life,</hi> Pſal. 42.8. As if it were ſaid, God the life of his childrens prayer is with them in their act of praying. They need not travel hundreds of miles to preſent (their Petitions on pilgrimage: the marrying of his body together, and the rejoycing over them, as a <hi>Bridegroom rejoyceth over his bride,</hi> Iſa. 52.4.5. proves Gods preſence at their heart-working-life. Here, here, I ſay, is perfection, when God in a perfect way viſiteth a perfect heart: the living man is as well able to lay aſide his breathing, as theſe are able to forbear preſſing on towards the mark, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14. or to follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God, having no pattern but the Heavenly Fathers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to imitate, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.8. being under the laver of that Blood which was ſhed by this eternal Spirit, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. Our perfection is in the life a working, it is yet <hi>perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting holineſs in the fear of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.1. and whilſt we
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:31711:14"/>
draw our natural breath, the blood of Chriſt in cleanſing will do its work, the fear of God its work, and our Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father will ſtand for our Pattern, and our Chriſt will be our life, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7.</p>
                  <p>There is nothing but it may be yet a perfecting in us, only our purchaſe by the blood of Chriſt is perfectly paid, and in that ſenſe it is finiſhed, and our ſalvation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken: if either the Tempter were dead, or we our ſelves ſtronger then <hi>Adam</hi> was in his innocency, or the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil day and hour of our temptation paſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. we might ſpeak of ſuch a perfection as admitted of no imperfection; but whilſt the Scripture is of uſe, <hi>let him that thinketh he ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth take heed leſt he fall;</hi> and we may (as the caſe now ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with us) with <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak of perfection and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction both in one <hi>Chapter, Phil.</hi> 3. If thou beeſt undefiled in the way, thy ſoul will be in this frame: 1. Thou wilt not endure to ſee the leaſt defilement in thy ſelf, without loathſome apprehenſions of thy ſelf, and running to that fountain which is ſet open for ſin and iniquity to waſh in, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.1. And 2. If undefiled in the way, thou wilt be always a running, and not careleſly ſleeping, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. but rather weeping with thy face thitherward, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.5. either for joy, ſhame, deſire, or all theſe; ſo ſtrongly will thy heart be ingaged to ſeek the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.21.</p>
                  <p>A fourth caution. Take heed that every one of you ſtrive by watching, begging of God, beſeeching one another to keep from among you <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage; this ruling one over ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with rigor, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.13, 14. which might not be one brother over another in the time of the Law. Reaſon firſt, becauſe that love which procured the ſhedding of Chriſts blood, hath cauſed his poor Members to be ſet as a Seal on his heart and upon his arm, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6. and owned them for his people, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.16. Therefore if thou haſt Gods love ſhed abroad in thy heart to conſtrain thee, afford it them out of thy breaſt.</p>
                  <p>A ſecond Reaſon why we ſhould not rule over our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren with rigour, is, we are, and ſo was <hi>Elias,</hi> ſubject to the like paſſions that any feeble, brother is, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.17. and thou mayeſt come to be remoted, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. and it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31711:15"/>
thy temptation may be this, that <hi>Satan</hi> may move thee to have low, contemptible, yea. (it may be) hateful thoughts of thy brother, and thou mayeſt have a Spirit of putting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and covering violence with a cloak, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.16. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heed of this temptation.</p>
                  <p>The third Reaſon, why not with rigour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Becauſe thou art not godly or Godlike in ſo doing: for he did not take thee at advantages when he might juſtly have cut thee off, but waiteth for thee that he may be gracious unto thee, and will wait upon all to that purpoſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.11. He cut none off ſuddenly, in a few days or a week, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thine offences to all advantages, that he might break thee off; he hath given contrary rules to that, to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Diſciples how to move towards their Brethren, <hi>Luke</hi> 17. the <hi>five firſt verſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let my fifth caution therefore be, That for no ſuppoſed advantage ſake, or fear of diſadvantage to the truth, thou dareſt ſtep from the Rule that Chriſt laid down, one jot; for if thou doſt, it is a judging of the Law-makers wiſdom and foreſight; as if he did not foreſee and provide in his rule for all following effects.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, It is an exalting of thine own wiſdom, in that thou thinkeſt thou ſeeſt cauſe to be a ruler further then he hath left a rule to guide thee by.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Thou mayeſt aſſay (in ſo doing) to prevent the fruit that God bringeth forth by contrary means. In this caſe how far might <hi>Abrahams</hi> imagination have fought againſt Gods command? He might have ſaid of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> he was the ſon of the Promiſe; and the Promiſed ſeed is in his loyns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Amongſt other Scriptures, I offer to thy conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. the 5. <hi>firſt ver.</hi> where after the poſition laid down in the 2 <hi>firſt ver.</hi> in the 3 following <hi>ver.</hi> he thus apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Take heed to your ſelves</hi> (as if he ſhould ſay, Here will be a dangerous temptation) <hi>If thy brother treſpaſs againſt thee, rebuke him; if he repent, forgive him; if he treſpaſs againſt thee ſeven times in a day, and ſeven times in a day turn again to thee, and ſay, It repenteth me, thou ſhalt forgive him.</hi> Where note, that the offenders heart is not to be judged by the offended. God allows thee nothing but his tongue to judge of in this
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:31711:15"/>
caſe; it may be his heart may more melt afterwards then at the firſt turning, by the offended's tenderneſs or other means: and the offended ought (from bare judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) to forgive him, if he do it as his duty, obſerving Chriſts rule; his heart may be opened with more love and tenderneſs to the Offender afterwards alſo, then at the firſt turn. However it is better to walk in ſelf-denyal in this caſe, and obſerve Chriſts rule, then to ſatisfie thine own offended ſpirit; however, if thy brothers heart and tongue ſhould not agree in his repentance, God hath not made thee a judg of evil thoughts, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.4. And the Apoſtles anſwered, <hi>The Lord increaſe our faith:</hi> which anſwer proves they had great need of help to ſtrengthen their faith to this purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>A ſixth Caution. Take heed of this Doctrine, That Saints do not ſerve God for ſalvation, but from the knowledge of ſalvation. This Doctrine not being rightly divided, hath been a ſtumbling block to many. Man ſince <hi>Adams</hi> fall is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly ſo proud, that nothing but the top of excellency will ſerve his turn, and therefore to be as gods knowing good and evil, tickled his mind. You ſhall hardly find one in a ſociety (men are in this point ſo heightned by the Tempter) that will acknowledge he cometh to God for ſalvation, though it be at the firſt hour of the receiving into ſociety. Men under this temptation are not willing to <hi>begin to ſtand without till the good man of the Houſe be riſen up,</hi> Luk. 13.25. but all judge themſelves finders from the ſelf-flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring conceit, before they have enjoyed the Lord Chriſt by manifeſtation. Few will own that there may be a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of darkneſs in one that feareth God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10. They had rather in this temptation compaſs themſelves about with ſparks, <hi>ver.</hi> 11, as if all had right to baptiſm only upon that account that is recorded in <hi>Act.</hi> 10. viz. <hi>Who ſhould forbid water that theſe ſhould not be baptiſed, that have received the Holy Ghost as well as we?</hi> And thoſe that enquired, <hi>What ſhall we do to be ſaved?</hi> had no right, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. Though it be certain they received the Holy <hi>Ghoſt</hi> after Baptiſm, and alſo it is certain, that at the firſt the Diſciples ſerved Chriſt as ſervants, though after they were owned by Chriſt upon a more full account, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.15. There was a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31711:16"/>
time when <hi>Paul</hi> knew <hi>Chriſt</hi> after the fleſh, which muſt needs be for ſelf-ends, or good that might come to himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; but after that, he knew neither man nor <hi>Chriſt</hi> any more after the fleſh, but wholly having his ſpirit of love and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light exerciſed upon them, to rejoyce in <hi>Christ,</hi> and to ſerve the creature, with the love of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhed abroad in his heart.</p>
                  <p>I would that all who are in Church-fellowſhip, upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Faith and Repentance, and have not as yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to aſſurance, would (with underſtanding) own their condition, it would make them <hi>give all diligence to make their calling and Election ſure,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.10. Therefore leſt Members ſhould ſplit themſelves upon this ſtumbling-block, ſhew your ſelves <hi>workmen that need not be aſhamed, rightly dividing the word of truth,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.15.</p>
                  <p>Caution 7. Whereas Diſputes hath been formerly, <hi>viz.</hi> about that time the <hi>Ranters</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> firſt ſprung up; ſome holding it to be their Priviledg (but not their Duty) to ſerve the Lord; I adviſe thee to aboliſh this Diſpute from thy Societies, and from your particular ſpirits: for it is the greateſt Priviledge that can be, to have a heart united to fear God's Name, whilſt they walk in God's truth, being inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in His way, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.11. Here is no liberty from Duty, to walk in God's wayes and in his truth, and yet a heart uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>God,</hi> and that to fear His Name; and from this very act is <hi>David</hi> ſet at liberty to praiſe God's Name, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.12, 13.</p>
                  <p>I demand whether it be not a Saints Priviledge to have a heart enlarged by God, and yet it is then to <hi>run the way of Gods Commandments,</hi> Pſal. 119.32. <hi>viz.</hi> enlarged and ſet at liberty from the pit of corruption, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38. from the horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pit, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.1. to be bound to <hi>Gods</hi> love and wiſdom, who hath provided Commandments that he knows ſerveth to unite thy heart to <hi>God;</hi> he hath commanded nothing but righteous things, which are according to the Divine Nature, that thou art (or art to be) partaker of, 2 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.4. and thou art (or art to be) joyned to <hi>God</hi> and one Spirit, that is to ſay, the breathings, love deſire, delight of <hi>God</hi> is to be thine, and thy ſouls delight to breath in them, and thus thou art
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:31711:16"/>
in union with <hi>God,</hi> in Chriſt Jeſus; ſo that the ſame things are now commanded by the Law of the ſpirit of Life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. which was by the Law of Sin and Death, <hi>viz.</hi> it had been Sin and Death to thee, if thou hadſt not done thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments which the Law of the Spirit of Life hath enabled thee to do; but they are a Law ſtill, and now having a heart ſet at liberty, the Commandments which were before a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, is now not made grievous by love: and if the love of God be a Saints Priviledge, it is nothing leſs then to bind us to our Duties; <hi>for this is the love of God, that we keep his Commandments, and His Commandments are not grievous to us,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.3. Lo, here is no freedom from Duty. <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>If the Son make you free, you are free indeed,</hi> Joh. 8.36. ſaid alſo, <hi>If ye love me, keep my Commandments.</hi> Here you ſee that love bindeth the freeſt people in the world to their Duty of obedience, <hi>Joh</hi> 14.15.</p>
                  <p>And when Chriſt proclaimed his yoke to be <hi>eaſie,</hi> and his burden <hi>light,</hi> He did not alter it from being a yoke and a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.30. but it is a ſweet burthen, when there is nothing ſave a conſtraining love upon thy heart; it is a ſweet yoke when thou art faſtened to <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> and his <hi>Saints,</hi> to tread one trace by love in keeping ſuch <hi>Commandments,</hi> as that the things commanded <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Saints,</hi> and thou in the unity of ſpirit loveth, upon account of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders love and wiſdom, how can ſuch Commandments be grievous? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.4. But if any ſhould further ſtill contend for liberty in this Caſe, let them know, that <hi>ſin is the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the Law,</hi> verſ. 8. and <hi>whoſoever committeth ſin is of the Devil,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.4. and let all who think they know God (whilſt they deſpiſe that which He and His Diſciples com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and practiſed) let them remember this word writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.4. <hi>He that ſaith he knoweth God, and keepeth not His Commandments, is a Lyar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As from this opinion that was ſometimes in the Church, (I deſire it lurk not ſecretly there yet) the <hi>Ranters</hi> and <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> ſprung, ſo alſo do now thoſe who are zealous in decking their bed of Love, which they (poor deceived ones!) under pretence of peace-offerings and reconcilement to God, in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31711:17"/>
performing the very Vows of their ſouls, <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.14. ſeek to draw Proſelites in a bed of ſolace with love, being ſo ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled (as they think) and covered ſufficiently, and beautified as with gifts and graces, verſ. 16. that they can hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others from the reproof of Truth, whilſt they are workers of iniquity; though they ſay they preach and caſt out devils in Chriſts Name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He that knoweth their works will call them ſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22, 23.</p>
                  <p>And alſo they have perfumed their bed with divers ſpices, <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.17. and it is too too true, they hold forth the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſome of thoſe ſpices, but not all; that Jeſus Chriſt in his Viſitation of His <hi>Spouſe,</hi> cometh perfumed unto His <hi>Spouſe-Bed,</hi> Cant. 3.6, 7. and theſe in the good Mans abſence will have other pleaſures and luſts then to obey their Lord; they have contracted a hatred in His abſence to his Rule and Government, and will not have it, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.14. and thus theſe poor deceived ones will be cut off, for making a perfume and ſmelling to it, in other places then where God and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple meet, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.35. to 38. which is in God's wayes, while they rejoyce in working Righteouſneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.5. <hi>viz.</hi> in ruleful obedience, where love to Chriſt is proved by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Commandments; and the love of God and Chriſt, together with their manifeſtation, is promiſed.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Libertines, tell them of walking in the wayes that Chriſt and His Diſciples walked in, and they will reply, <hi>If God let them ſee it, they will obey.</hi> May not <hi>Solomon's</hi> harlots ſay as well (when the good Man of the houſe is come home) who will inſtruct her? for that is Chriſts practiſe with His <hi>Spouſe, Pſal.</hi> 32 8. ſhe will forſake all her wooed Proſelites, and ceaſe to heal, defend and cover them, and will no more counterfeit a perfume to perſwade them that Chriſts favour of his oyntments is amongſt them, but but will come to the good man, and walk with Him in obedience to His <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> and abide in His love, is He hath kept His Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Commandments,</hi> and abides in His love, <hi>Joh</hi> 15.10. So that if it be truth (as ſurely it is) they refuſe to obey; when the good Man of the houſe is come home, they muſt then ſee it, though they ſhut their eyes, and blame his abſence for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:31711:17"/>
their diſobedience, whoſe preſence would let them ſee, and with this excuſe fall faſt aſleep in the arms of him who rules in the children of diſobedience; whilſt he furniſheth them with all counterfeit evidences of good, as if God were in their hearts all this while, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. the words are theſe: <hi>So that he, AS GOD, ſitteth in the temple of God, ſhewing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that he is God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the firſt evidence that he furniſheth them with may be this, <hi>viz.</hi> That Chriſt hath put His beauty upon them: for the beauty of Chriſt may be put on one, and that by Chriſt, and yet they play the harlot with it, <hi>Ezek</hi> 16.14. here is the work of the Prince of the air, in a diſobedient heart, to find wayes for <hi>Iſrael</hi> to diſobey God, and give up a ſoul to Luſt, and ſo play the harlot, even as if ſhe were opening her heart or her legs, for Chriſt to take His pleaſure in her, and ſhe in Him.</p>
                  <p>A ſecond evidence of him who rules in the hearts of the children of diſobedience, is, in the pleaſure of the Plant which is but a ſtrange ſlip; It muſt needs be a ſtrange ſlip, if your wayes be not thoſe wayes which Chriſt and His Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples walked in, for three hundred years after Him: your wayes muſt then be your own, and of your own chuſing, and ſtrange from Chriſts, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 36.34. <hi>viz.</hi> The teacher with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to thee and himſelf, may plant in thy heart with thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or with thy ſoul, a diſobedient ſlip, ſtrange to Gods word, it being not there to be found; and for all thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, thy portion will be deſperate ſorrow in the end, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 17.11, 12. here is a deceitful work of the ruler in the heart of the children of diſobedience.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He can make you lean upon the Lord, and ſay, <hi>Is not the Lord amongſt us? no evil can come to us,</hi> Mic. 3.11. he can make thee bleſs thy ſelf in the name of God, with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of freedom from evil.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whilſt thou art aſleep, he can furniſh thee with a flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit, that cauſeth thee to dream, and healeth thee in thy diſobedience; and ſo in your preaching and hearing one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, you have nothing but healing and pleaſure, and love to tell one to another in diſobedience: whereas he who hath
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:31711:18"/>
Gods word, will preach it faithfully, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.28. and for his pains ſhall be caſt out of your Societies: ſo unwelcome is the thoughts of obedience (to Chriſts Commandment) to thoſe who dream they ſhall be ſaved without it: Although the true Saint be not only moved to obedience for ſalvation ſake, but for loves ſake; and thus by maintaining that which Chriſt neither taught nor practiſed in his worſhip, or at leaſt, by gathering of what Chriſt taught, by pieces and ſnatches, and leaving the reſt, <hi>viz.</hi> by taking that which will, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that which will not ſerve the luſts of a proud Society, that thou mayeſt hold ſome union with them, thou fighteſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lyon of God, and at the beſt (in this thy dream) doſt but think thou eateſt; when Truth it ſelf ſhall awake thee, and thou be convinced of thy diſobedience, thou wilt find thy ſelf hungry, <hi>Iſa</hi> 29.7, 8.</p>
                  <p>And if any ſtrive to awake them out of this their dream, wherein they have neither Truth nor Reaſon for their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, they will ſay, <hi>Let me alone with my Religion, and I will let you alone with yours.</hi> Whereas if they would not thus har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den their hearts, but let Judgement come forth to Victory, what violent wreſtling would there be in them? what ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and enquiring would their hearts be filled with? what weeping with their faces towards God and his wayes would melt their ſouls? <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.5. and not asking (as now they do) with their hearts ſet againſt Gods ways, to ſee if they can find any word (which if it do meet them) it muſt be by the ſpirit of deluſion, miſ-interpreted, to defend them from obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God and his ways. Is it not juſt, that theſe ſhould have ſtrong deluſions, that they may believe lies? 2 <hi>Theſ</hi> 2.11. Will not this properly one day be ſaid unto them, <hi>Bring forth the blind people that have eyes?</hi> Iſa. 34.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <p>Therefore I adviſe all men to diſclaim any thing in Religion, that judgement cannot give thee to underſtand and hold forth to others, (when though ſhalt be asked a Reaſon of the hope that is in thee) to be truth, though a Spirit ſhould offer to teach it thee.</p>
                  <p>The tongue cannot move beyond the ear, being both natural, &amp; theſe can both be but miniſters of the natural Underſtanding; pen and eye are ſervants to the ſame, and can ſhew but utterable things: take but away the uſe of theſe under a pretence of a Spirits teaching, and the natural under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and his ſervants are uſeleſs, and cannot glorifie God, which was the end of their Creation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>VVritten by <hi>H. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:31711:18"/>
            <head>THE DESCRIPTION OF THE BEAST.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is to be premiſed, That the VVhore and the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet, being that they are all appertaining to one Babel, or Members one under or in another, all of one ſpirit, all of the refuge of lies, to which men flee from truth, and are to be ſwept away together, and all at agreement with Hell and Death, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 28.15 to the 19. and all come to an end by one power, when the VVhore ſhall be judged, and the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet caſt alive into the lake that burneth with fire and Brimſtone, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20.</p>
            <p>That this Deſcription may the better appear, we are firſt to obſerve that this Beaſt is ſettled by the Dragon, who is the Devil and Satan, and that this ſettlement is his inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility: he hath the ſubtilty of the old Serpent imployed to hide him, that he might live. And</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let us obſerve that he is like a Leopard, in which ſence he is beautiful; and his beauty appeareth moſt to the minde and intellect, becauſe the ſpirit of Satan, that is, his father, his Setler, yea, and his Life, is an applyer of himſelf to the ſoul, being an inward worker; for his deceiveableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, is in them that periſh, where he cauſeth delight and glory, and ſeeming happineſs, to fill the minde;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:31711:19"/>
but conſulteth with Truth and Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, His likeneſs is never ſeen nor underſtood in his tearing actions, but as if ſomething elſe had done them, for then he uſeth a Bears foot, and a Lyons mouth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider that when the Scripture ſpeaketh of his mouth being like a Lyon, it doth not ſpeak of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, as tongue and teeth, (for his teeth hath ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther likeneſs where they are deſcribed, as in <hi>Daniel,</hi> they are called <hi>Iron teeth</hi>) but mouth, which includeth all the act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing powers therein, whoſe inviſibleneſs is ſet forth by the ſupremeneſs in dominion &amp; ſtrength that the Lyon hath over all Beaſts; and that this beſt reſembleth the Lyon moſt in his mouth, where his lordlyneſs, ſtrength and victoriouſneſs lyeth in the month: in the mouth is firſt a preparing of food for the ſtomach, and the ſecond, utterance of the voyce: by the ſtomach, the minds ſatisfaction may be meant; and in this, his proſperity is great; for <hi>their eyes ſtand forth with fatneſs, they have more then their heart can wiſh,</hi> Pſal. 73.7 to 11. Being that this Beaſt is the imbodyed power of Satan, whoſe name is <hi>Abaddon,</hi> we cannot think that his ſtomach can digeſt any thing but deſtruction and cruelty, and all helliſh food; and, Satan-like, deſiring the deſtruction of all men: and to this purpoſe this ſtrong mouth worketh. Note that his ſtrength in voyce cannot be any thing elſe but Eloquence (which is the enticing words of mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1, 17.19. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.26.) and Lies, which is the very ſtrong way they prevail in, to the deſtruction of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.10. <hi>Zach.</hi> 10.2. (take heed Clergie that this word be not a witneſs againſt you) in this lyeth great ſtrength to keep his dark hidden ſettlement, <hi>viz.</hi> in Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and Lyes, of which he wants neither.</p>
            <p>Look about you, to ſee if you can ſee him when he is a working and preſent, but with Eloquence and Lyes he will be hidden from you, for he is always hid in the preſent tenſe, that is to ſay, though he yet is, he is not, (which muſt needs be underſtood whilſt he cannot be ſeen) but it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent enough he was, then men may ſee plainly what he hath
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:31711:19"/>
done in the Preterperfectenſe, for he brings all his blind ones to had-I-wiſt. The words that are written in <hi>Rev.  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  was</hi> and <hi>yet is,</hi> being there is no Scripture that can ſhew when this Beaſts Creation was, or when he was not, can ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of no other ſence, but the very plain words as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: the words <hi>is not,</hi> being a plain contradiction to the words <hi>yet is,</hi> for one of the twain muſt needs be a contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the other, except expounded. Then <hi>[is not]</hi> is well underſtood to mean <hi>[is not viſible,]</hi> being that he is alwayes hid from ſeeming what he is, when he teareth, and deſtroyeth, and deceiveth, with his Beares foot, and his Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mouth: for if he were known to be what he is, the very knowledge of him would take away his ſtrength, for then neither Magiſtrates nor People would do his works: his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearings are ſeveral; one when the confeſſion of Chriſts Name cauſed him to rage to the deſtruction of the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, when there was no diviſion of Papiſts and Proteſtants, being hunted our there, the very oppoſing of the Papiſts Tranſubſtantiation and other innovations, cauſed him to rage to the deſtruction of them that engaged againſt them, though both of them confeſſed the name of Chriſt; and then the Papiſt might have ſaid unto the Proteſtant, Yea, if your ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings had been for confeſſing <hi>Chriſts</hi> Name, as the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Martyrs were, then your ſufferings had been right; and now here in <hi>England,</hi> being hunted thence by day-ſpring va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Truth, he rageth againſt thoſe that would have <hi>Chriſts</hi> Baptiſm, and all His Goſpel-Order, ſo that as Light breaketh forth, he followeth that, roaring with Lyons mouth, and tearing with Bears foot all the children thereof, as Truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth them, he being ſpirited by the ſame Satan or Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Truth that was under the Law. So that a man may beſt know him by the bloody ſides he hath torn the ribs out of, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. and by his paſt acts of cruelty. When Mr. <hi>Love</hi> was preſent with his fellow Traitors, in the glory of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Clergy-man, who would have thought that they had a heart, to the overthrow of many thouſands, to raiſe VVar and Blood-ſhed, onely to advance a Scotiſh Presbytery, which Beaſt had then a bloody face, but now it is hid again
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:31711:20"/>
under a ſuppoſed learned Godlineſs? and how blind was poor <hi>England,</hi> that could not ſee it to be the cruelty of this Beaſt, when Pulpits provoked their Natives in her own Bowels, for Religion to murther one another? in which horrid drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 23.33, 34. the (eſteemed) godlyeſt men (becauſe they were moſt believed) ſent forth moſt men to this ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>Let us again look upon this Lyon-like mouth, that can be ſtopped with nothing but the blood and fleſh of the flock of the ſlaughter, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.3, 4. where the howling of the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, and the roaring of Lyons are mentioned both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; where <hi>Iſraels</hi> Clergy are reputed pitileſs, ſlayers and fellers of the flock, and hold themſelves not guilty, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord, for I am rich;</hi> (ah poor <hi>England!</hi> how dangerous are acts of cruelty amongſt thy ſhepherds, when they are labourers for licenſe to deſtroy for Religions ſake?) this was the condition of poor <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who was ſometimes as dear in Gods ſight as <hi>England,</hi> when it was at the beſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.25. <hi>There is a conſpiracy amongſt her prophets, in the midst thereof, like a roaring Lyon; they have devoured ſouls, they have taken the treaſures of their pretious things, they have made many widdows in the midſt thereof.</hi> VVe may alſo look upon our Clergy, how they band together, to get, if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſuch Parliament-men as might be as teeth in their heads, (Chriſt takes no ſuch care to exalt His Goſpel by world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Magiſtrates) it is apparent that theſe Prieſts took no care how many widdows they made, or of devouring ſouls; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs our Pulpit-VVar to maintain liberty for themſelves to lead ſoules blindly, that were blind to deſtruction: but the pretious things they will bave, or elſe they will ſue and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs him that dare not for conſcience ſake pay them for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring ſouls, and many poor labouring men, and widdows, and children, that are conſtrained to fit with bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pottage, whilſt their labours and profits are required to feed them, and cloath them with the pretious things of our Nation: Is this love and pity, the Law of Heaven, where the ſervants in the Goſpel ſhould live upon giving and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving? no, no, it is the contending and diſtreſſing Law of hell
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:31711:20"/>
rather: take heed (good People) of ſuch ſhepherds, if you once come to have a glimpſe of them, ſearch and look far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for if you delight in ſuch, hear and obſerve, that <hi>he that loveth</hi> as well as he that <hi>maketh</hi> a lie, is without the City of Salvation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. Of the enmity of a Spirit ſomething like this Beaſt, I found in the mouthes of ſome of our <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colnſhire</hi> Clergy, who (though they had not forty ſhillings a yeer, according to the Statute of Free-hold) were ſwarming to chuſe the Knights of the Shire; I deſire that any of the reſt when Truth provoketh them, and will not be found to ſerve their turns, be of a better ſpirit; for theſe could bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter digeſt lying, then to be reproved for lying.</p>
            <p>About thirty years agon, when I was perſecuted by the Biſhops, wandring from my dwelling place, I came to <hi>Spal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> where I did remain a little time; where (being in the company of two or three Chriſtians) I had occaſion to look upon the 139 <hi>Pſal.</hi> we being only talking together, I did read, <hi>I am wonderfully and fearfully mad,</hi> inſtead of <hi>I am wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made,</hi> I not at all being preaching then, as the Lyar did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port: ſome that failed in their Duty of taking things in the beſt part, reported it; notwithſtanding, at the ſame time I did correct my ſelf, and own the true reading: and this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port being gotten into the neſt of the Clergy, and there hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by hatred &amp; ſcorn, brought forth this enlargement, that I ſhould preach it as a Doctrine: But I know not what. It came to paſs, at the chuſing the Knights of the Shire, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Jan.</hi> 10. a great company of Prieſts being got together in <hi>Lincoln</hi> Caſtle, I coming neer where they were, one of them comes by me with a boy-like behavior, and cryeth, <hi>I am wonderfully and fearfully mad:</hi> to which I ſaid nothing, and he paſt into the crowd of them; and another, either a Prieſt or one of their dear Berns, ſeeing the firſt did not provoke me to ſpeak, accuſed me (by the name of <hi>this fellow</hi>) for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Doctrine; but what, I could not gather, his words were ſo confuſedly uttered, onely <hi>wonderfully and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully mad;</hi> for there is none of them agreeth in words what the Doctrine was; and ſo turned his back, to whom <hi>I</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Art thou not aſhamed to maintain the Prieſts lies,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:31711:21"/>
and then turn thy back, when thou haſt ſpoken the words? but he turning his face and averting the ſame, the Synod of them turned to me with out-facing countenance, to whom I ſaid, <hi>I ſtand here to maintain the Truth, againſt the whole Synod of you:</hi> And whereas I might expect ſomething to be ſaid that might make that which they ſaid probably appear, firſt one of them, and then another of them cryed, <hi>Hout him, Boyes, hout him,</hi> all the reſt ſtanding ſilent, approving (for they did not reprove) what the two ſpake. Alſo Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant of <hi>Boſton</hi> told me, That one that he looked at to be a godly Miniſter, told him, That when ſome cryed, a <hi>Hall,</hi> a <hi>Hall,</hi> I cryed, a <hi>Halter,</hi> a <hi>Halter;</hi> which here by my pen and heart, in the preſence of God, I deny, for I did not ſpeak thoſe words, nor any words to the contempt of Mr. <hi>Hall,</hi> nor had ever in my Life an offended thought at the man. Obſerve, if the ſuppoſed godly of them bend their tongue like a Bow for lies, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.3. and the active men among them be ſo inclined to mutiny, as the Reader may judge how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſuch words were, at ſuch a time and place: Are they not like to be Members of the aforeſaid Beaſt, and like that company of Prieſts aforeſaid, that muther in the way by conſent, (for theſe ſought my undoing, either by Mr. <hi>Hall</hi>'s hands, or the multitudes, and to ſtain my repute) according to the interpretation of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.21. and alſo guilty of ſlander, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.20. and making a man an offender for a word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.20, 21. and ſhall according to that word, be brought to nought, conſumed and cut off, if they repent not.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:31711:21"/>
            <head>The coming forth, and Progreſs of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> hitherto.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe holy Scriptures foreſeeing,</l>
               <l>Devourers for to grow.</l>
               <l>Amongſt &amp; out of church of Chriſt, <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2 12 <hi>Acts</hi> 20.30</note>
               </l>
               <l>Doth truly ſtile ſuch ſo.</l>
               <l>As Lyon, Bore and Wolfe,</l>
               <l>And dumb and greedy dogs,</l>
               <l>That ſelfneſs, honors, beaſt-like wealth,</l>
               <l>Doth wallow in like hogs</l>
               <l>In mire, yet ſtill fild with fears,</l>
               <l>Their only loved prey,</l>
               <l>By ſtrength of day-ſpring valiant truth</l>
               <l>Should taken be away.</l>
               <l>Their Lepord-like, with Lyons mouth do grin, <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2</note>
               </l>
               <l>And paw of Bear, with Dragons ſtrength ſtretcht out,</l>
               <l>A child of truth, in the act of covering</l>
               <l>Their worrying paw, leaſt men ſhould ſpie,</l>
               <l>Their naked, ſhameleſs, beaſtial cruelty.</l>
               <l>With Chriſt ſheeps cloathing whil'ſt they can deceive <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> v: 15.</note>
               </l>
               <l>With that, when not, they Magiſtrate ask leave,</l>
               <l>That they may uſe his ſword, and then they'r bold,</l>
               <l>Though inſide wolviſh nature men behold,</l>
               <l>To tel truth's children that they muſt not prate,</l>
               <l>But put into their mouths, elſe they will make <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mica</hi> 3.5</note>
               </l>
               <l>War againſt them: whom God doth love, they hate.</l>
               <l>From ſomtimes Church of Chriſt</l>
               <l>Did Pope and Prelate ſpring,</l>
               <l>From Pope and Prelate, did</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:31711:22"/>This Presbyter begin,</l>
               <l>From Presbyter did Independant fly,</l>
               <l>Yet members ſtill of one body</l>
               <l>Made, ere they knew in infancie,</l>
               <l>But Scripture Baptiſt doth them all deny.</l>
               <l>For the good old way that Jeſus walked in <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 7.16.</note>,</l>
               <l>And the Apoſtles taught repenters to begin <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38.</note>,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Hereupon the ſpirit of the beaſt rouzeth up himſelf again.</head>
               <l>Yea thinks the Quakers ſpirit, then will I</l>
               <l>All that is called God or worſhiped deny <note n="g" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.</note>
               </l>
               <l>For where by order <note n="*" place="margin">by making falſe order.</note> I can have no place,</l>
               <l>I muſt exalt my ſelf to the diſgrace <note n="*" place="margin">viz. in his deceived ones, who exalt the ſound of name, but have (being ignorant of) the nature of the law of God and Chriſt.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Of God, oppoſing order of his face;</l>
               <l>Though God be the God of order.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Plainneſs of truth oppoſite to the beaſts myſticall pretences.</head>
               <l>GOD ſent his ſon in fleſh to come,</l>
               <l>True naturall blood to ſhed,</l>
               <l>And did ordain his death to be</l>
               <l>In ſimple man, bake't bread.</l>
               <l>And Vine fruit wine that men do drink,</l>
               <l>Which God and man doth chear,</l>
               <l>When in his ord'nance ſpirit joynd</l>
               <l>The price of Chriſts blood dear,</l>
               <l>Shown to hold forth his death for ſin,</l>
               <l>Until he come again,</l>
               <l>That is gone up true advocate,</l>
               <l>Our cauſe for to maintain.</l>
               <l>Where holy God and ſinful man,</l>
               <l>By Chriſt a treaty hold,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:31711:22"/>Who takes our prayers, and there to God</l>
               <l>Our miſeries doth unfold.</l>
               <l>And doth return into our hearts,</l>
               <l>The fruits of his blood ſhed,</l>
               <l>True pordon, ſtrength, comfort and joy,</l>
               <l>By ſpirit witneſsed.</l>
               <l>Who doth with blood and water joyn</l>
               <l>One witneſs manifeſted <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.5 8.</note>,</l>
               <l>In Gods one way whil'ſt men obey,</l>
               <l>Repent and be baptiſed;</l>
               <l>And then expect pardon of ſin,</l>
               <l>And holy ſpirit Gods gift <note n="b" place="margin">2. <hi>Acts</hi> 38</note>,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt that our loves is prov'd to Chriſt,</l>
               <l>In making it our ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</l>
               <l>For to keep all Gods commandments,</l>
               <l>Where Scripture comfort dwells <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4</note>,</l>
               <l>With Son and Father manifeſt,</l>
               <l>Where men are not Rebels <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 14 21.</note>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Hereupon the ſpirit of the beaſt proceedeth.</head>
               <l>Thinks diſobedient ſpirit, I have</l>
               <l>No ſhare in this ſtrong Saviour,</l>
               <l>Il'e cry down Lawes and holier be</l>
               <l>Then all that formes do favour,</l>
               <l>In the eyes of thoſe that have the love</l>
               <l>Of ſimple truth denyde.</l>
               <l>Il'e ſerve their luſts and them perſwade</l>
               <l>They need not to be ti'd.</l>
               <l>I ſtrong deluſion can command</l>
               <l>Affections into tears <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8 14</note>,</l>
               <l>And cauſe men for to lean on God,</l>
               <l>And ſo free them from fears.<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mica</hi> 5.11</note>
               </l>
               <l>And cauſe men to proteſt to God,</l>
               <l>That they'l obedient be <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 42.6</note>,</l>
               <l>Yet his commandments to deny,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:31711:23"/>And ſay it is not he <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 43. i, 2</note>.</l>
               <l>For in right ſteps of humbleneſs <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 17: 11</note>,</l>
               <l>They ſhall ſeem after God to preſs.</l>
               <l>And though by Chriſts knowledge they ſcape,</l>
               <l>Through luſts the worlds pollution <note n="g" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet</hi> 2: 20</note>,</l>
               <l>Yet Gods commandments turning from,</l>
               <l>They're faſt in my poſſeſſion,</l>
               <l>Although that they his way forſake,</l>
               <l>They holineſs may hold <note n="*" place="margin">The ſtrength of deluſion li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in their ſeeming to themſelves &amp; others to hold forth their formal holineſs:</note>,</l>
               <l>For I will ſpirit them my ſelf,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt they're fearleſs and bold,</l>
               <l>I can my ſelf transforme</l>
               <l>Into an Angels light;</l>
               <l>And there maintain the light within</l>
               <l>The diſobedient wight <note n="a" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11: 14 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.</note>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Truth ſpeaketh.</head>
               <l>As righteous they muſt ſure appear,</l>
               <l>Whilſt they can have the Skill</l>
               <l>To ſeem as Chriſts Apoſtles right,</l>
               <l>And preachers of his Will <note n="b" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11 13.15</note>:</l>
               <l>Theſe were ſo far convinc't,</l>
               <l>As to diſclaim prophaneneſs;</l>
               <l>But love of truth did not receive,</l>
               <l>To bring them to obed'ence <note n="c" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2</note>;</l>
               <l>Self-love did them provoke,</l>
               <l>Leſt they ſhould damned be,</l>
               <l>Or of ſalvation be deny'd,</l>
               <l>Prophaneneſs for to flee;</l>
               <l>Doth it avail (ſaith they)</l>
               <l>To ſave us? let us ſee:</l>
               <l>All other Scriptures they throw by</l>
               <l>As uſeleſs for to bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Deluſion ſpeaks.</head>
               <l>Therefore to them Ime ſent <note n="d" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2 11. <hi>compar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with</hi> 10 <hi>Verſe:</hi>
                  </note>,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:31711:23"/>Such lies they ſhall believe,</l>
               <l>As me their inward Teacher to</l>
               <l>Prefer, though God they grieve <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.6.</note>;</l>
               <l>Before that ſimple Chriſt,</l>
               <l>That Scripture-writing gave,</l>
               <l>That men might read &amp; know his law,</l>
               <l>And ſure inſtructions have <note n="f" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1 19, 20 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 3.17.</note>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Truth ſpeaks.</head>
               <l>The Man of God to make perfect,</l>
               <l>And furniſh him throughout,</l>
               <l>There is a rule to know Gods will,</l>
               <l>None need of it to doubt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Deluſion ſpeaketh.</head>
               <l>In mans imagination</l>
               <l>Ile frame a lawleſs Chriſt,</l>
               <l>And ſet my ſelfe up there as God,</l>
               <l>And in his name be hi'ſt;</l>
               <l>Ile cauſe theſe to aſcribe to me</l>
               <l>What ere to God is due,</l>
               <l>And to my inward motions,</l>
               <l>To flye from Scripture-view.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>[<hi>Remember Ahabs caſe,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.23.]</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Truth doth, and will conclude.</head>
               <l>When beauteous holineſs appears,</l>
               <l>In ſweetned-ſoul the dew of youth to bring,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 110</note>
               </l>
               <l>In morning womb, it never fears</l>
               <l>To own its Jeſus Lord and King;</l>
               <l>That God-begotten, Virgin-born,</l>
               <l>That crosfide fleſh was crown'd with thorn,</l>
               <l>Hath ſaving power, and law-giving,</l>
               <l>In perſon, place and time,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:31711:24"/>No true man can deny this thing,</l>
               <l>And ſay he 's without crime.</l>
               <l>That doth ſalvation to himſelf apply,</l>
               <l>Whilſt that obedience he doth clean deny,</l>
               <l>Though faith and bapti'm in one book be writ,</l>
               <l>Yea in one Chapter, and in one Verſe too,</l>
               <l>Deluſion ſaith he can the faith out pick,</l>
               <l>And leave the bapti'm for ſome elſe to do.</l>
               <l>Thus ſelf-love his ſalvation minds</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt love of righteouſneſſe thinks fit,</l>
               <l>To hate iniquity betimes.</l>
               <l>The Oyle of gladneſs with his Chriſt to get <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 45.7</note>,</l>
               <l>And thinks nothing for himſelf to imbrace,</l>
               <l>To be too low, carnal or baſe.</l>
               <l>That his Jeſus to his Apoſtles gave</l>
               <l>For Church direction; but will tread the trace,</l>
               <l>With Chriſt and his Diſciples to his grave.</l>
               <l>And knowes when's left his body, then that he</l>
               <l>From 's bodyes worſhip, not before is free.</l>
               <l>If our great God by ſuch a lowly thing,</l>
               <l>As blew in fringe would <hi>Iſrael</hi> mind</l>
               <l>Of their obedience to their Lord and King <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Num<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 15 38</note>,</l>
               <l>That they might not to their own heart,</l>
               <l>Nor to their eyes be ſeeking,</l>
               <l>With ſpirit of diſobedience dark,</l>
               <l>(Though light calld) go a-whoring,</l>
               <l>Then think not baptiſm &amp; breaking bread,</l>
               <l>Mean Lawes, by Chriſt b'ing uttered;</l>
               <l>Flying to holier ſpirit they think, then Chriſt,</l>
               <l>That doth and will exalt himſelf the high'ſt,</l>
               <l>Within the diſobedient child,</l>
               <l>That is by ſpirit, but not by God beguil'd.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:31711:24"/>
            <head>To all Law-givers and Magiſtrates.</head>
            <p>WIth the ſubmiſſion of a poor worm that is under your feet, (that you may behold what God hath given to my heart to write a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to men, and that you may avoid all provocations to that horrid ſin of building up <hi>Sim</hi> with blood, <hi>Micah</hi> 3.10.) I tender this treatiſe to your view, hoping that you will not deſpiſe the words of him that is as much your underling, as any maid-ſervant to her Maſter, (though they may <hi>Contend</hi> with ſome of you, <hi>Iob</hi> 11.13.) Being I am heartily engaged by Chriſt Jeſus my maſter, to diſſwade all men from adhering to mans inventions, or devices, in and about the worſhip of God, becauſe they are ſo dangerous to prince and people in the land of my nativity, as is proved in the 106. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> &amp; the 29. Verſ. and <hi>Pſalm</hi> 99.8. <hi>Iſa:</hi> 66.5. and many other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>And from declining the exact rule of Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles laid down in the bookes of the New Teſtament only; under which grace we are, and not under the Law of terror, <hi>Heb:</hi> 12: 21.</p>
            <p>This poor Supplyant of yours, to whom God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven grace to be faithful, is willing (I hope) amongſt many others, <hi>to ſtand in the Gap,</hi> by ſhewing to you and all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and praying to God for you and it, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.30. compared with the 28. Verſe, the very way, by which an end muſt be put to the proceedings of the <hi>reſiſters of the truth,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3: 9: Viz. by the diſcovering their folly to all men; to which purpoſe, this poor-ſervant of Chriſt Jeſus hath written this treatiſe againſt this firſt Beaſt that ariſeth out of the Sea, <hi>viz.</hi> the Church that hath his power maintained, and his worſhip exerciſed by the ſecond Lamb-like horned beaſt, that is more like a Lamb then the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:31711:25"/>
firſt, and ariſeth out of the eatrh, <hi>viz:</hi> the world, and yet he holdeth up the firſt beaſts power and worſhip by Magiſtrate ſword, the place that the firſt aroſe out of yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no ſuch power, his Lamb-like horns being the ſtrength that prevaileth with the Magiſtrate to uphold him, <hi>viz:</hi> a repute of holyneſs and innocency, in which he exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, therefore as a Lamb, or as one in ſheeps cloathing, and in the pretended name of the Lamb Chriſt, he taketh pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by the Magiſtrate to conſtrain rich and poor, ſmall and great, bound and free, to worſhip, &amp;c. <hi>Revelations</hi> 15. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where there is a conſtraint upon all into one worſhip, we may well ſuſpect that it is the power of that beaſt, who is the very powerful life-giver to the bare Image of the firſt beaſt which Image, if it had not the Magiſtrates pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to conſtrain it, it were life-leſs, and therefore called the Image, becauſe it hath neither Scriptures authority to provoke, nor power to conſtrain, ſo that this beaſt is but a <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agon</hi> at the beſt, that cannot ſtand without mans art or power to uphold it, and ſhall certainly fall when Gods arke of teſtimony is brought to it, and this is the laſt beaſt that ſhal be at enmity with my Maſter Chriſt Jeſus, and this is the ſame ſpirit with the firſt, who is the old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and Satan, whoſe whole body conſiſting of beaſt, whore, and falſe Prophet, as head, body and taile, ſhal in the end periſh together, <hi>Revelations</hi> 19.20.</p>
            <p>The beaſt was once wounded by my Maſters providence and power, when he died upon the Croſs, where he <hi>ſpoiled principalities and powers, and made ſhow of it openly, Col.</hi> 2.15. the vertue whereof is his deadly wound to this day, and no Salve that the beaſts healing flatterers hath (though for a time it giveth eaſe to the blind ſleepy conſcience) can make this deadly wound unmortal, <hi>viz.</hi> thoſe Prophets ſpoken of in <hi>Ezek</hi> 13.9</p>
            <p>But when triumphant truth, the beaſts mortal foe, ſhal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, to make manifeſt what this wounded beaſt is, that can never look upon Gods word to examine his own ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but he ſo much feeleth there the ſoarneſs of his mind, as that he dare not in it proſecute his examination, he ſhall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:31711:25"/>
be dead by that act, and taken out of the way, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. and by how much truth looketh forth, by ſo much this beaſt is ſick of his wound; ask your ſelves when truth appears; where is lyes? are they not all dead and gone; then impudencie and out-faceing of lyes muſt needs ceaſe, when God ſhall <hi>deſtroy the face of the covering of all people, and the vail that is ſpread over all nations, Ezek.</hi> 25.7. the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſcovery of him is his wounding; therefore let thoſe of the Clergie that loves to be Maſters of all people, upon the account of godlineſs, contrary to Chriſts counſel, <hi>Math.</hi> 23.10. look about them, for Chriſt Jeſus <hi>woundeth the head out of the houſe of the wicked, by diſcovering the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to the neck, Selah, Hab.</hi> 3.13. for then their ſtanding will appear whether it be of God or no; then their begging for liberty to perſecute thoſe that dare not feed them, and honour them, will be at an end, when Gods out-caſts are viſibly provided for, and the <hi>oppreſſor ceaſeth, Eſa.</hi> 16.4. then thoſe that made lyes their refuge, vvhen they fled from the written word to mens invented <hi>may bees</hi> will be utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undone, when the patient, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.36. not haſt-making beleivers, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 28.16. is upon their ſure foundation, <hi>then the Hail ſhall ſweep away all the refuge of lyes, and the water ſhall overflow the hiding places, Eſa.</hi> 28.17. So that it muſt needs follow, that the weapons of our war-fare are not carnal, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. but mighty through God, ſo that the ſword of the Magiſtrate hath no ſuch ſtrength againſt this beaſt, as mighty truth hath; therefore be wiſe O ye Kings and Rulers of the earth, as it followes in the ſecond <hi>Pſalme</hi> 10.11.12. <hi>Verſes,</hi> take heed of perſecuting any for Gods ſake, although they be preſented to you as deceivers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.36. and ſeditious, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.5. For was not Chriſt and his Apoſtles ſo preſented to their perſecutors, it is better to take Chriſts counſel, <hi>viz.</hi> let both grow together till Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, then that the blood or diſtreſs of any one perſecuted Saint ſhould lie at your door; Chriſt diſclaimed any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſt in your kingdom in the dayes of his fleſh, and ſet an example of obedience to God, in being under your au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: and his Apoſtles commanded ſubmiſſion to you,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:31711:26"/>
and to pray for you, and we are yours, ſubjected to you in all civil obedience; ſo do you refuſe to have autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in Chriſts Kingdom, and be you there ſubjected to him; and as he ſaith, <hi>My Kingdome is not of this world,</hi> ſo ſay you, that your Kingdome is not over his Church, and let his Laws be in your eys as they are in truth, ſo wholly, by which he governeth his Church, that man cannot add to them, or amend them; it is poſſible to help forward a deluſion by perſecution, making the erronious preſume that they are martyrs for Chriſt when they periſh in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon upon religious accounts, (and then if you do that to them for Chriſts ſake, or for Religions ſake, for which you have no rule in Gods Word, it will be then (if God give you not repentance till the day of Judgement) that hee will come to ſay to you, Who hath required this at your hands?) but never to provoke them to love the truth, or make them willing by mans, but by Gods power, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. Yet if you go about to drive them that Chriſt is a wooing and beſeeching them by the mouth of his Apoſtles, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. you may come at the trouble of your conſcience in the hour of death too too late to repent; but we as our duty is, do pray &amp; indeavor that no ſuch thing may fal upon you</p>
            <p>And in the words of the Apoſtle, We beſeech you to be reconciled to God, and not oppoſite to his gracious pardoning mercy, in going about to take from man, or to make uſeleſs the forgiveneſs of that blaſphemy againſt the Father and the Son, by the lips of Chriſt, now in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of his Goſpel granted and proclaimed, Mat. 12.31. for without repentance there is no forgiveneſs; and how can any repent when the ſword of the Magiſtrate hath cut him off? [Concerning this there hath been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in a former Parliament] <hi>Paul</hi> took not that courſe, he did not flie to the Magiſtrate to have <hi>Hymenus</hi> and <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> cut off, but he took a courſe that made them capable of learning to amend, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. which had not been lawful for <hi>Paul</hi> to have done, had not Chriſt in his Goſpel taken away the rigor of that Law which is written in the 24 of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> and the 16. And upon this Goſpel ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:31711:26"/>
Chriſt told <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> they knew not of what manner of ſpirit they were of; For the Son of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.55, 56. when they of Samaria would not receive Chriſt; therefore if any ſort of men like theſe companie of Prieſts, that <hi>murder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the way by conſent,</hi> that are ſpoken of in <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.9. (for it cannot be thought theſe Prieſts took away tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral lives, by temporal weapons) ſhould tempt you to mend thoſe Lawes that Chriſt and his Apoſtles left for Church-government, and give puniſhment for breaking them (exceeding the ſeveritie of the merciful Law-givers Edicts) which tend to the peoples deſtruction; when Chriſt the <hi>wiſer then Solomon</hi> (and therefore wiſer then any prince or Synod that ever was, or will be in this world) gave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch puniſhment for breaking his Lawes, as tended only to mans ſalvation, neither hurting their perſons, eſtates, nor liberties; The Lord ſtrengthen your hearts, and give you courage to reſiſt them who care not that much people periſh by you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hands, yea and by war and bloodſhed, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then their Honor and eaſie fatt-conditions ſhould go down, and they ſhould miſs to be Lords over mens conſciences, and Gods inheritance, Witneſs <hi>Love</hi>'s trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>There is no fore-ſight like Chriſts, nor nothing ſhall come to paſs even to the end of the World which he fore-knew not; and upon this account he left ſufficient provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the being and wel-being of his Church: The very ſeed of the Devil when it ſprang up, Chriſt would not have his Diſciples pull it up, leſt they ſhould pull up the Wheat alſo, thinking it ſafer to let manie wicked Imps grow, then to venture the deſtruction of anie poor childe of God; Then be not overcome to let anie be deſtroyed for Chriſts ſake by the petitioners for deſtruction, though thoſe they vvould have deſtroyed are preſeneed unto you for the Devils Ims, being you have Chriſts directions in the caſe, <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.28, 29. I do hereby earneſtly ſupplicate you to conſider, that England is not more dear in Gods eyes then ſometime Iſrael vvas, and may come to be (if it bee
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:31711:27"/>
not alreadie) as far falne from grace as Iſrael vvas, vvhen there was four hundred prophets for one <hi>Micah,</hi> 1 King. 22.6. When the zeal of <hi>Jezabel</hi> was ſuch, that ſhe main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained four hundred and fifty prophets, and four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred prophets at her table all at once, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18, 19. and theſe falſe prophets that would flatter, face-painting <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabels</hi> and wicked <hi>Ahabs,</hi> bare all the ſway in Iſrael at that time, when as priſons and threatnings of death for the truths ſake, was the portion of all the <hi>Micah</hi>'s <hi>and Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi>'s, and to be hid in a Caves, and fed with bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; it is good to have ſuch a holy jealouſie, as may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke all that fear God, to pray for the Land and the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers thereof, and to warn our great ones that are Preiſt-feeders, to look to it, leaſt their zeal deceive them not, and that they be not found of that number, <hi>that prepare a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for that troope, and furniſh a drink-offering for that number,</hi> that are ſpoken of in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 65.11. to 16. and when Chriſt makes this great diſcovery, their zeal be found no better then <hi>Jezabels</hi> was, it muſt needs be thought that her Preiſts were confident, elſe they durſt never have joyned iſſue with <hi>Elias</hi> about the tryal of their God, and his God; therefore let the truth adviſe you not to truſt, for there is both learned Papiſts and learned Proteſtants, and one or both of them muſt needs be in an error, but bring all to the law and to the teſtimonies, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 8.20. and if they deviate one jot from Scripture, and give an invented <hi>may be</hi> in the room of it, beleive them not, but take notice that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is able to furniſh a man of God throughly, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.6. and there is no need of mans invented <hi>(may be)</hi> to be joyned with it; and leaſt our great ones way, and their Preiſts way, or peoples way, ſhould be a way of wickedneſs, they are intreated to follow <hi>Davids</hi> example, who was as right as any King or great man can come to be now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, yet he was earneſt with God to try him, leaſt his way was a way of wickedneſs, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 129.23.</p>
            <p>It is undoubtedly true, that when the Prophets cry out to the Magiſtrates for harms to their neighbours, for religion ſake, they are not of that ſpirit of Chriſt Jeſus that came not to deſtroy, but to ſave mens lives, and if poor
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:31711:27"/>
               <hi>England</hi> or the rulers thereof be willing to hear this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, then thoſe ſad words may beſpoken of it, as was ſpoken of Iſrael, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.31. <hi>viz.</hi> The Prophets propheſy falſly, and the Prieſts bear rule by their means, and my people love to have it ſo, but what will you do in the end thereof?</p>
            <p>And ſo it is, that we being under another ſpirit then <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> was, deſire no harm to thoſe deſtroyers from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate; No no, he might be quiet in his civil imployment, if our enemies would trouble him about matters of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no more then we do, but we deſire that none may be welcome to you, that tempt you to keep us from the free &amp; plain uſe of the Scriptures of Chriſt, in the ſimplicity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, without ſpoyling us by Phyloſophy or learned troops of figures, which are vain deceit when they are uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth, <hi>Iob</hi> 2.8. to which Scriptures we appeal utterly, and that by the help of the ſame ſpirit that wrote them from all inventions of men, whether brought forth by Synods or Aſſemblies of Divines, or any others, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my duty in the name of Chriſt my Maſter, I warn you in the love of God (who is love) that you ſuffer the word of God to run and be glorified in the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoundedneſs, that Chriſt and his Apoſtles left it, without changing the Laws thereof, or giving any other puniſhment for breaking the Laws thereof, then Chriſt and his Apoſtles left order for in the Scriptures; man can as harmleſly endeavour to change the Orgins and light by which the natural eye ſeeth, as to amend what Chriſt and his Apoſtles left for his church government throughout all ages to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>O ye Law-Givers and Magiſtrates, as my ſoul is a pitty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your inevitable and dolorous danger, whileſt you or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you are meddling with the apples of Gods eyes, or whileſt you are tempted to endeavour to mend the perfect Law of God <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 19 knowing the tempter is ſo hidden under Chriſts name, &amp; hath ſo prevailed with former Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates, as that they by the then Clergies preſent perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, have been as it were the ſlaughter men of Chriſt &amp; his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:31711:28"/>
Apoſtles, and all his ſuffering Saints to this day, it being the word of Chriſt to take away trouble from the ſufferers hearts; when they know whileſt they are under your hands, they are under the alſupporting and comforting power of God alſo, who leaſt that theſe things ſhould come upon them at unawares, foretold them that they ſhould be had before Kings for his names ſake, and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever killeth them ſhall think he doth God ſervice, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.4. Loe here, is not here a propheſy ſutable to a ſeeming god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Clergie for Gods ſervice ſake, to bring to paſs by temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations? take heed Magiſtrate, and know that it is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God, and for your help in this caſe, conſider that there are many and ſweet directions in that new Teſtament, that is ſealed with Chriſts Blood, how ſufferers ſhould behave themſelves, but not one how perſecutors of Chriſt Laws ſhould behave themſelves, in bringing either the body or eſtate of any Heretick to diſtreſs for Chriſts ſake, which proves that there is no Plaintiffes but all Defendants, or rather Pasſives for Chriſts ſake, in Chriſts flock, the ſheep have no means nor ſtrength to commence one action againſt the Wolfe.</p>
            <p>Alſo conſider how it would pleaſe you, if your ſervants ſhould for their honour, riches and wealths ſake, by their inventions only, bring forth as your mind, another rule to govern your houſe by (and that ſtated only upon ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments) then you had left by plain expreſs commands in writing, without any difficulty; and the Lord make the dutiful and loving endeavors of this poor ſervant, to be one means amongſt many others, to hold you in a ſweet apprehenſion of Chriſt and his Laws, that you may receive the bleſſing that is pronounced out of Chriſts mouth, <hi>viz: Bleſſed are they that are not offended in me.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:31711:28"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>CHriſtian Reader, thy relation to our Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, rendereth thee choſen, and called,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.4</note> and faithful;* ſo that whereſoever thou behold this ſubtil beaſt that creepeth under the pretence of God and Chriſt, and ſo hide himſelf, it is thy duty to hunt him; for it is poſſible thou may hunt out ſome members of Chriſt out of him, <hi>Ier.</hi> 16.16. that are ſet down in his riches and pleaſures, and there hidden from the feeling of Chriſts life in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and bring them forth to be wayfaring men, that they may travel in the high way, and the way that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led holy, where the blesſing is not more entailed, or not ſo much upon the man learned, as upon ſimple ones, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and fooles; (<hi>viz.</hi> in the worlds account) <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 35: 8. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.4. being that diſcovering is death to him; ſo thou haſt nothing to fight with, but the lip of truth, which ſhining upon him, will melt him as the Sun melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Ice, and is a Cordiall heart, rejoycing life, and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting preſence of Chriſt in thee, whileſt thou beleiveſt in God, and uttereth his praiſes to his and thy enemies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, who is made up of a lump of lies, frozen as it were together by Satans cruelty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35: 25: when he is made manifeſt, he muſt needs be ſlain, for then no man will as God or godly, believe or receive a known enemy of God and godlineſs:</p>
            <p>Thou muſt not follow him with carnal weapons, as clubs, provoking mutenies againſt him, and whips, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſpoiling of goods, thoſe are his weapons; but thou muſt be ſo far from rendering evil for evil, that when any member of this beaſt ſtriketh thee on the one cheek, thou muſt turn to him the other alſo, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 10: 3.4: yet the weapons of thy warfare are mighty through God, as prayer, tears, ſword of the ſpirit, blood of the covenant, the whole armour of God ſpoken on in the 6: <hi>Eph:</hi> 11: and in as much as he calls it the whole armour of God, it
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:31711:29"/>
proves that God hath never a peice of armour but that for thee to uſe, in whoſe name then can priſons, &amp;c. be uſed by thee, I know thy heart and thy labour goeth both together, thou haſt a tender regard to thy Chriſts honour, therefore if thou diſcover any countertfeit coming forth in his name, thou with heart, and pen, and tongue, wilt cry out of him, according to the meaſure of the Talent thou haſt received; and becauſe the love of God is ſhed abroad in thy heart, thou wilt be an eye of diſcovery to, and a hand pointing at this beaſt, for thy weak brethren, that they fall not into his pits and ſnares, and as God loved the world, ſo thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God-like, wil uſe the love of God ſhed in thy heart to love it alſo, yea thy very enemies in it, that thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the terror of the Lord, <hi>viz.</hi> againſt this beaſt, wilt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men to look to their doings, and ſtanding, (for we muſt all appear before God) leaſt they periſh with this beaſt and falſe Prophet, which falſe Prophet muſt needs be a ſuppoſed (but not) godly Clergy, which defendeth them that receive the mark of the beaſt.</p>
            <p>The perfect love that <hi>Moſes</hi> had, was to work all the means of ſalvation by prayer to God, and inſtructing the people, yea when they were in acts of rebellion againſt God, reviling himſelf and <hi>Aaron;</hi> who was but a figure of our Lord Jeſus, who was upon the act of the Jews eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſalvation, and Gentiles, when they were in the act of crucifying him; they ſcoffed and peirced him, he prayed for them; and of the like mind muſt thou be Chriſtan Reader, to thoſe that are taken Captive of the Devil to do his will, thou art to recover out of his ſnares, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. though their hearts be enraged againſt thee, they make ready their hearts as an oven, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 7.6. when the darts that comes out of their ſouls, (<hi>viz.</hi> terrible words and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring actions) though poyſoned with Aſps envy and rage, and ſelf-tormenting agonies, they being ſhot at thee, fall into thy ſoul (thou receiving them by faith) all quench <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.16. by the love that faith worketh by, thy quieted mind, returns prayer for them and glory to God, rejoyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that thou art counted worthy to receive the rage of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:31711:29"/>
men, which in thy ſoul turneth to Gods praiſe, but can do thee no further harm, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.10: be encouraged for thou muſt overcome, thy heart muſt not be inſlaved, thou muſt hear thy teſtimony for thy Lord and ſaviour, <hi>Rev:</hi> 15:3: if thou mean to ſing his praiſes in heaven; and thou haſt no other weapons but the word of thy teſtimony, and the blood of the Lamb, (and wo wil be to them that ſight in Chriſts quarrel with any other weapons) the one is to keep out ſubjects and ſpirit of <hi>Abaddon;</hi> who fight with car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal weapons, and provoking temptations to deſtroy one-another, (which you wil eaſily ſee if you compare the 38: of <hi>Ezek:</hi> 10: with <hi>Rev:</hi> 20:8:) thy heart being ſprinkled with the blood of the Lamb, they would deſtroy thee too if this blood did not ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p them out, but no child of God can be deſtroyed, though his body periſh, when his heart is held up in its rejoycing delight in God; priſons, and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and all perſecution, being but keyes to open the hear to God more abundantly, and meſſengers to bring Gods preſence into it, to keep his heavenly court there; then thou wilt not be provoked at thy enemies further then to pittie them, and pray for them, and do them good; the other is the Scriptures, which is the word that Chriſt thy Captain fought this beaſts ſpirit with, when he bare teſtimony againſt him with <hi>it is written,</hi> and that is the word of the teſtimony, <hi>it is written,</hi> will find all his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers out, it will approve the proved perfect way of God, and diſcover every falſe way; and that thou and I may walk in the fear of God, and comforts of his ſpirit, with the Churches of Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 9:31. and alſo in the comfort of the Scripures, our way being there recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15:4: we behaving our ſelves wiſely in a perfect way, waiting for the coming of the Lord Jeſus to us, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 101: 2: may walk with a perfect heart is the deſire of thy companion, in the faith, and under the croſs of Chriſt:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H: H:</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:31711:30"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>REader,</hi> if thou haſt a deſire to take him in a ſnare that reproveth in the Gate, <hi>Eſa:</hi> 29:21. and endeavoureth to make ie matter for thy hating or perſecuting ſpirit to work upon, that theſe things are written againſt thee, as the Phariſees did againſt my maſter Chriſt, (unworthy I to call him ſo, yet he having given me grace to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and commanding his loving kindneſs into my heart, and opening my heart to receive his father and himſelf, and ovvned me, and cauſed me to ovvn him) I am bound to tell thee that thou mayeſt ſhevv thy ſelf of the Phariſees ſpirit, and as one of them by ſo doing.</p>
            <p>But the children of truth follovving the example of their Lord and Lavv-Giver, endureth contradictions of ſinners, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.3. vvithout heart-riſing-malice, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing evil, or perſecution to them, but their rule is to love their enemies, &amp; pray for them that perſecute them; the Scripture cannot ſhevv any Diſciple that ran to the Magiſtrate for help againſt any diſputant; the Diſciples of Chriſt have all one ſpirit, even the ſame that <hi>Steven</hi> had, that the gain-ſayers could not reſiſt the vviſdom of it, and not the Magiſtrates ſvvord at their call, neither dare they lay it upon the right eye of their enemies, that they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dare look upon nor ſpeak truth becauſe of it, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.17. though it be the gain-ſayers portion, yet it is not from Chriſts Diſciples, if they ſhould not be inſlaved that are fed, and maintained by the Magiſtrate, they could not be idle ſhephards, but vvould break through all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to look upon the light, though it coſt them vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever harm the ſvvord that lieth upon their eye could do them.</p>
            <p>Truth and thoſe that are of it begotten, are vvilling to come to the light, to have their practiſes and opinions ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, for it delights to be exactly ſearched and examined, and the more contradictions are endured,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:31711:30"/>
and the current of them not ſtopped the more it ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</p>
            <p>I adviſe thee to underſtand that this little book is not written againſt any perſons, but ſuch as are ticntured with the ſpirit of that beaſt, it is a hunting to diſcover for, this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit cannot be attributed to Presbyterian, or Independant, or Quaker, or Baptiſt, no not to Pope and Prelate alone, or at all except they have the acts and inſtruments of cruelty men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by them, which are the cogniſance of the fourth beaſt, that hath no certain creatures form, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.7. as the other of the three had but was <hi>dreadful and terrible,</hi> to ſhew it was a perſecutor, <hi>it had great Iron teeth, ten horns,</hi> which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of cruelty; it brake in peices, devoured and ſtamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the reſidue, <hi>viz.</hi> all but it ſelf; here is acts of cruelty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; O how like this beaſt is thoſe religious people that would deſtroy all religions but themſelves, by the Magiſtrates hand for non-conformities ſake to themſelves; but this beaſt is in every place, yea in the very Temple of God, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.1. and whereſoever there is either power, of man ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be <hi>Abaddon,</hi> and <hi>Apollons</hi> ſubjects, or of ſpirit that oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth either ſpirit or form that agree together in the true wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and worſhip of God, or whereſoever that oppoſing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit maintaineth his breath, there will ſome time or other ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the <hi>Tallands</hi> or the <hi>ten horns,</hi> or the ſtamping power, or ſome deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, that is in them that periſh, yea though it be the very ſubtilty of him that can transform himſelf into an Angel of light, and theſe are all members of that ſelf hiding beaſt.</p>
            <p>Whereſoever or among what people ſoever this beaſt hath loſt his honour in one form, he taketh up another, yea and rather then fail of his purpoſe denyeth all formes, ſo that it may be ſaid he was, and upon his hiding himſelf, he is not there where he was as viſibly and formally the ſame, and yet is the ſame ſpirit of that beaſt that ruleth in the children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, that alwayes either oppoſeth the plainneſs or the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualneſſe of Chriſts commands, one while ſaying they are too low or fooliſh, or carnal as (water baptiſm, &amp;c.) for thoſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:31711:31"/>
that look after ſpiritual light to one, another while exalting a falſe form, another while added form without either ſpirit or life; and thus he playeth bow-peep, appearing on the one ſide and on the other, here and there, when and where, he is diſcovered changing his form, or peeping out without any form, and it is apparent that he aſcendeth out of the bottomleſs pit, becauſe no rule that Chriſt hath given in his word can meaſure him, he dſiclaimeth that when it would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover him, and then telleth you that the place he cometh from is the movings of a ſpirit, and in this it is bottomleſs, becauſe no right reaſon nor meaſuring line can declare, where or what, or when this ſpirit will make his progreſs, or try his work that refuſeth all tryal but himſelf.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, let not the Clergy be enraged, that this writing hunteth after this beaſt, if it be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Clergy or Presbitery in <hi>England,</hi> it may be it wil be found in <hi>Rome</hi> and ſome other land, let them help me to hunt him out. If they do not rather compell by the Magiſtrates ſword into conformity, then convince by ſound doctrine; the gain-ſayers, <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus</hi> 1.9. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. and not deſire them to be rooted out of their dwellings, to be caſt into priſon, to have their goods ſpoiled for want of conformity to them, if they be content not to be chief of all that come forth in the name of God; <hi>viz.</hi> not to give Laws to all, ſo that none may preach without their authority, and let Gods authority without mans ſerve the turn, if they can be content that any man caſt out Devils, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.39. if they can be quiet in mind to ſee others preach Chriſt, that have not authority from them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in it, though he be preached of envy, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.15 if they be without all the forenamed inſtruments and acts of cruelty, nor have no heart to deſire, nor ſue for power to force conformity to them by the Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates ſword, then they are no members of the Beaſt that this book pointeth at.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:31711:31"/>Hovvſoever none can deny but that ſome Presbyterians and Independants are held in their forms, upon account of riches and honour, or for ſome ſelf-engagements ſake, although moſt or all may not be ſo (vvhich I am afraid are) there is novv ſo much light abroad according to <hi>Daniels</hi> Propheſie <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.4: that if there vvere ſuch a povver upon them as could make their hearts manifeſt, as one day there ſhal be, ſome of them muſt needs ovvn ſome part of the ſpeeches that are ſpoken in this book to be the very thoughts of their hearts, &amp; that they take comfort and have their ſtandings maintained from the cauſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted there, and other-ſome the reſt, and ſome all; hovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I am excuſeable, becauſe the ſpirit of God out of the mouth of Jeſus Chriſt my maſter, in the undvidiing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion ſaid, <hi>Wo to you Scribes and Phariſees Hypocrites,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome of them proved believers they were then the guides (though blind ones) &amp; teachers of <hi>Jſrael,</hi> a people that God loved ſomtime as wel as ever he did <hi>England;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Chriſt reproving Lawyers, ſpake wo to them in general, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.46. though ſome of them proved good men, as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph of Arimathea,</hi> and <hi>Nicodemus, &amp;c.</hi> then it is posſible that <hi>England</hi> may be as blind led, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> then was, for the Phariſees and Lawyers was as learned then as ours now are; therefore Reader take heed that thou let not thy heart riſe againſt this book by unconſiderate prejudice, read it, ponder it to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Take heed of retaining that ſpirit that thinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wiſe enough to controul plain commands of Chriſt in Scripture.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Alſo if the plaines and ſimplicity be that that offended thee in Chriſts Lawes, read <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.6. and ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider whether the practiſe of the Apoſtles and Diſciples for 300. years after Chriſt be not a good expoſiter of the Law, and that thou need not go to ſpirits or Angels for a higher expoſition, againſt their plain practiſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider in thy mind whether any Statute recorded in the Scripture can be repealed, but by a Statute there
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:31711:32"/>
alſo recorded, and then take heed of changing Chriſts Laws upon mans authority.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Do not believe becauſe the falling away is great, that therefore the Law of baptiſing beleivers is cancelled, for if the command were not yet in force there could be no fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from it, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21</p>
            <p n="5">5. Underſtand that whoſoever falleth away, &amp; yet are religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, muſt needs have ſome inventions of man by Satans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward working, either that the Rule is not exact enough, then meditate <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.16. or that it is too ſtrait, then carry thy meditations to the written Word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.28. and there pitch down thy Standard for truth.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If truth of God ſtir thy mind to trouble, and the Word carry a ſharp edge, rightly applyable to thee, take heed that Satan work thee not into the rage of revengeful perſecution, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.10. and then thou may come to approve thy ſelf to be a Chriſtian Reader, which is the deſire of the ſervant of Chriſt, who is a well-wiſher to the whole Creation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:31711:32"/>
            <head>A true Reproof of <hi>W. S.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving known your diſcretion in other things I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but wonder that you ſhould ſeem to ſuppoſe that you have any thing like an Anſwer to <hi>H. H.</hi> in your Book; but much more ſhould I marvel that you ſhould ſay, It is hard to draw Wine out of thy Lees; Which is as much as to ſay, It is hard to anſwer that which you go about to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. And though you ſee your ſelf blundered in what you are about to anſwer, that you would go on <hi>(viz)</hi> to heal thoſe that Truth woundeth, but that I conſider that when once your heart cometh to engage in error, then wilful ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance tempts God, and hardens your hearts againſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent truth of God, then yours ceaſeth to be an outward ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle diſobedience, but it is an inward heart working, God-tempting (though ignorant) Error, which is not charged in this place of <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10, 11, 12. with ignorance of God but of his Wayes, and in this appeareth a heart of unbelief, in departing from the living God, when men are wilfully ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and have a heart ſet againſt his Wayes: Wherefore herein you prove your ſelves to be of the ſhameleſs genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſpoken of in <hi>Ier.</hi> 6.10. your ſpirit is not aſhamed to take the Name and Title of God, and you are not aſhamed to ſay you are moved by God, when indeed you are moved by the Evil One, you giving, and he taking the Name of God; or rather the uſing your lips to exalt himſelf above God, with 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. and alſo in that he maketh you his voice by his own Authority to proclaim null the Laws that God made by Jeſus Chriſt, and without any Warrant from Chriſt or his Apoſtles, crying down that vvhich they taught and practiſed, either they or you muſt needs be of Satan, being that the Scripture ſaith, <hi>If we, or an Angel from heaven teach
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:31711:33"/>
unto you another Goſpel then what we have preached to you, let him be accurſed, Gal</hi> 1.8. You ſay in your Book, (I deny) <hi>I am made to ſtand a witneſs againſt thee in the power of the Lord,</hi> vvhilſt I hold up that Goſpel. What ſelf-exaltation is here! What proof is here of your matter? Here is great ſwelling Words; do you think your Spirits Authority enough, ſo that he need not to uſe Scripture to prove his matter by when he is queſtioned? Then he ſeems in this, as in other things, to be above Chriſt by his own exaltation, for Chriſt when he met vvith your ſpirit in temptation, though he be the Son of God, yet uſed Scripture, ſaying, <hi>It is written;</hi> and in his Word by the mouth of <hi>John,</hi> appealeth to Record, ſaying, <hi>There are three that bear record on earth, the Spirit, Water, and Blood, and theſe three agree in one;</hi> but your Spirit is ſo far from agreeing, that it oppoſeth two of them, wherefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the Spirit of God; your Spirit cometh forth in its own ſingle Witneſs, and denieth to be tryed by Scripture, or any thing elſe but it ſelf. You try all your matter by that you call the light vvithin, the natural man, &amp;c. of vvhich light your ſpirit is the transfotmed Angel, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14 and things are like to go on in his ſide in his ovvn Court. We acknowledge the light vvithin the enlightned man, vvhich agreeth with the Scriptures, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.32. compared vvith 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17. but not before illumination; this is the light that enlightneth every man; but vve muſt not acknowledge it but where it is: It is good to anſwer Tempters by ſeeing the image or ſuperſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though Tempters are more general. It is certain, there is ſomething called a light by Chriſt, that is in the unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man, and may be darkneſs, <hi>Matth</hi> 6.23. Surely this muſt be yours; for you own yours there, and vvould have all jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by that, and neglect Chriſt and his Apoſtles rules in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. And now to be ſhort, Friend, you have not found out one particular in all my Writings, whereunto you might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your ſelf as a juſt matter of your reproof, therefore you fell upon me with many foul revilings, onely there is a miſtake in the quotation, I not being at the Preſſe my ſelf to correct it, the place ſhould have been 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. for which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:31711:33"/>
you take him in a Snare that reproveth in the Gate, and maketh a man an offendor for a word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.21. yea, and that a word miſtaken onely; and that you do with moſt foul inſultations. In matters of the World he that ſhould proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his Neighbor for vvitneſſing the truth, when he onely miſtakes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he place and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and upon that point, would be known amongſt men as a cunning Knave.</p>
            <p>As for the matter you made ſhew to anſwer, you have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it all the go by, yet you will be in Print; Well, according to <hi>Solomon</hi> in <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.5. I have anſwered you; and according to his counſel in Verſe 4. I ſhall not anſwer you except you ſhew more Wiſdom; you have asked me no queſtion but what are plainly prevented in my Writings, if you had eyes to ſee it, you might ſee it, therefore I refer all to the judicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that ſhall read both Books. Again, you make ſomething of the word <hi>[Carpenters Son]</hi> but that is your miſtaking ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance; for it was he that the Jews vilified by that Name, who is the Saviour of the world, and Law-giver to Saints; and as they reproached his meaneſs by that Name, ſo you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the meaneſs of his Laws by the Name o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> outſide Law, carnal, unſpiritual things, as not high enough for him that exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped. Therefore the VVord is a proper alluſion to you, you and the <hi>Jews</hi> both vilifying Chriſt and his Laws as too mean for you.</p>
            <p>Again, you play upon the word, <hi>[Taking it upon me as my duty]</hi> you need not, for it is a Scripture phraſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.31. and whoſoever is a VVitneſs for the Truth, taketh up the Croſs, and upon him Chriſts burden, which to do is my duty; the word you ſee will warrant the phraſe, and that is more ſure then your As God his movings.</p>
            <p>I write againſt a Spirit and People in diſobedience, and I bended my writings againſt the thing wherein the deceit lay; I did perſonally aſperſe no man, but thou haſt miſſed the point, though thou comeſt forth as a man provoked, and one in union with that Error I reproved, and haſt brought forth my Name and dwelling-place, that thou mighteſt reproach
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:31711:34"/>
me with railing terms, upbraiding me with what men had done unto me, and art to be reproved by <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50 19<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 20 and <hi>Jude</hi> 8, 9, 10. Is not this perſonal animoſity? Have you not need to plead for perfection that do ſuch things? Do you think your Spirit that hath ſet you about this, is the ſpirit of God, or no: You muſt needs call this either envy or malice, or both: Is this any proof for your matter, that you give folks to think you anſwer? This is as impertinent as all the reſt, even ſo is thy calling that light in the natural man (of which Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.23. <hi>How great is that darkneſs</hi>) the light of Chriſt, and averring that I ſpeak againſt it; the Lord will uphold my good Name, though thou wouldſt blaſt it, and make me content to go through thy evil report, and be glad to ſee thee penitent and obedient to God, that thou and I may enjoy that one life and truth together with the Apoſtles and Diſciples, and that God-man that dyed upon the Croſs (and is now with his Father, and our Father, in heaven) which he gave in the dayes of his fleſh, and now maintaineth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Written by an unworthy Servant of God, who in Gods perfect way waiteth for viſitations of that Spirit that is ſent from the Father and the Son, by that Man Jeſus who is in Heaven in his eternal and unchangeable Prieſthood, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.24. <hi>H. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:31711:34"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. <hi>4</hi> line <hi>5.</hi> for talents read talands, l <hi>6.</hi> for peak r. beak, l. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> for Charts r. Church <hi>P. 12</hi> l. <hi>4</hi> after the word Diſciples, r. truth ſpeaketh, l. <hi>20.</hi> after the word mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hr when that Statute is as the mouth of ſome invetera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Clergy-men, to hold mens eſtates in at their pleaſure, <hi>P. 16.</hi> l. <hi>15.</hi> for Eccleſiaſies r: Nehemiah.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
